<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble examination of a printed abstract of the answers to nine reasons of the House of Commons, against the votes of bishops in Parliament. Printed by order of a committee of the honourable House of Commons, now assembled in Parliament.</title>
            <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E164_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871466</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871466</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156961</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156961)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 29:E164[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble examination of a printed abstract of the answers to nine reasons of the House of Commons, against the votes of bishops in Parliament. Printed by order of a committee of the honourable House of Commons, now assembled in Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 77, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for P. Stephens and C. Meredith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Cornelius Burges.</note>
                  <note>A reply to "An abstract of those answers which were given in the Assembly of the Lords in the High Court of Parliament" by John Williams, in defence of "Reasons of the House of Commons why Bishops ought not to have votes in Parliament", which were dated 4 June 1641.</note>
                  <note>K3r in two settings. Line 8 has (1) "it was good policy" or (2) it was godly policy" and signature-mark "K" of K3 is (1) under the "b" of "bare" or (2) under the "d" of "stand".</note>
                  <note>With errata at foot of K4v. Variant: K4v partly in a different setting, without errata.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Williams, John, 1582-1650. --  Abstract of those answers which were given in the Assembly of the Lords in the High Court of Parliament.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156961:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN HUMBLE EXAMINATION OF A <hi>PRINTED ABSTRACT</hi> OF The Anſwers to Nine Reaſons of the Houſe of Commons, AGAINST <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>otes of Biſhops in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order_to_print">
                  <body>
                     <p>Printed by order of a Committee of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, now Aſſembled in Parliament.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>P. Stephens</hi> and <hi>C. Meredith.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156961:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156961:2"/>
            <head>AN HUMBLE EXAMINATION OF A Printed ABSTRACT of the ANSVVERS given to Nine REASONS of the HOUSE of COMMONS, Againſt the <hi>Votes of Biſhops in Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="reason">
               <head>I. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe it is a very great hinderance to the exerciſe of their Miniſteriall Function.<note place="margin">To this <hi>Reaſon</hi> a foure-fold <hi>Anſwer</hi> is ſent abroad.</note>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>1. Is is not ſo much hinderance as their convening to Generall Councels, Synods, Convocations, Aſsemblies, Claſſes, and the like, in all the Churches Reformed, or otherwiſe.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Convening to Generall Councels, Synodes, &amp;c.</hi> when need requireth, is a proper part of their Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156961:3"/> Office, and ſo cannot rightly be termed any <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to their Miniſteriall Function</hi> at all. For then, although they be enforced to be abſent from their particular Congregations, they doe ſtill move with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their owne proper Orbe, for the more publike Service of the Church: and ſo they may with more reaſon expect a bleſſing on it. But when they <hi>Vote in Parliament,</hi> as Peeres, in Civill and Secular Affaires, touching Trade, Merchandize, and other particulars of State policy, they be Eccentrick, and out of their owne Sphere, and Calling. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt needs be not only ſome hinderance, but, <hi>a very great hinderance to the exerciſe of their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Function:</hi> becauſe, to qualifie them to give ſuch Votes, with judgement, they muſt neceſſarily beſtow themſelves moſt, if not altogether upon the ſtudy of, and ſearching into all thoſe Secular matters which in Parliaments be, or may be debated and voted, and in the inquiry into all thoſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and deepe myſteries of State, wherein, all that vote in the Houſe of Peeres, ought above all others to be moſt converſant; which cannot ordinarily bee attained, without ſpending moſt of their time and ſtudy thereupon: <hi>Si enim velit Epiſcopus, ut caeleſti pariter &amp; terreno Regi placeat, ad utrumque ſe officium dividere, certe Rex caeleſtis, qui ſibi vult ex toto corde, tota anima, tota virtute ſerviri, miniſterium divinum non approbat, non diligit, non acceptat. Nam nec terreni Principis ratiocinia quiſquam dimidius ſufficienter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrat;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Matth. Parker <hi>Antiq. Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. in</hi> Huberto <hi>ex</hi> Wil. Nubrig.</note> as a learned Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> out of another grave Author, hath obſerved.</p>
                     <p>And ſithence, to be able to give a <hi>Vote</hi> in the <hi>Lords</hi> Houſe of Parliament judiciouſly, and for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156961:3"/> of the publike, requires ſuch conſtant induſtry, daily obſervation, and no ſmall experience of all kindes of ſecular affaires, with their ſeverall caſuall turnings, and viciſſitudes: I cannot ſee how Biſhops; voting in that Houſe, can avoid one of theſe three evils, either they muſt give their votes ignorantly (and ignorance uſually runs wrong;) or corruptly, to ſerve other mens turnes, be they right or wrong, or els they muſt neceſſarily bend moſt part of their lives to ſecular ſtudies and imployments, to which they were never bred, from which their Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Function ſhould exclude them, and for which many godly Biſhops and others, beſide ſundry Councels, in all ages have condemned them; many of thoſe Ancients having alledged that Scripture, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>(Nemo militans Deo, implicat ſe negotiis ſecularibus, &amp;c.)</hi> to this very purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>For more expedition, I ſhall only name ſome of thoſe Authors and Councels. <hi>Cyprian. Epiſt</hi> 66. <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xta Pamel. Can.</hi> 6. <hi>Apoſt. apud Zonaram. Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag.</hi> 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 16. <hi>Concil. Chalced. Oecum. Seſſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Can.</hi> 3. <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 110. <hi>Greg. Magn. Dial. lib</hi> 1. <hi>Praefat. Excerpt. Egberti Can.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; Can.</hi> 57. <hi>Concil. Calchuth. Can.</hi> 10. <hi>Anſelm. in Concil. Weſtm. ut videre eſt in Guli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elm. Malmsb. de Geſtis Pontif. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Mat. Par. Hiſt. Angl.</hi> in the Caſes of <hi>Walter</hi> B. of <hi>Durham,</hi> in time of <hi>Will.</hi> the Conq. and of <hi>Hubert</hi> Archb. of <hi>Cant.</hi> in <hi>Ric.</hi> 1.</p>
                     <p>Yea, we ſhall find this ſharply condemned by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prelates themſelves. <hi>Corp. Iur. Can. diſt.</hi> 88. And <hi>Othobone</hi> the Popes Legate here, in <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. his time, cenſured it, and provided againſt it, as <hi>vitium horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> Conſt. Legat. cap. <hi>Cum honeſt.</hi> But I leave them.</p>
                     <p>See alſo <hi>Tindall</hi> in his Tract of Obedience of a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156961:4"/> Chriſtian. B. <hi>Hooper,</hi> on 8. Command. B. <hi>Latymer,</hi> Sermon called the <hi>Plough.</hi> B. <hi>Iewel,</hi> defence of <hi>Apol.</hi> par. 5. chap. 4. diviſ. 2. <hi>Mat. Parker,</hi> Archb. of <hi>Cant. Antiquit. Brit.</hi> in <hi>Huberto,</hi> where he is very large, ſharp, and ſolid in this point. Take a paſſage or two, becauſe his Booke is not in every hand. <hi>Neque enim, ſi verum judicare volumus, in Republica Chriſtiana quicquam ſani atque integri ſeculum illud</hi> (Richardi primi) <hi>tulit. Fictaque &amp; adumbrata Religionis ſpecie propoſita, totus Clerus in ſceleribus, muneribus, honori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; rapinis, neglecto penitus verbo, impune voluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Hujus mali origo ab hoc profluxit, quod contra Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxorum Patrum decreta, Clerus nimium mundanis ſe negotiis immiſcuit.</hi> Then hee goes on to ſhew a fearefull example of Gods vengeance upon one of them, who had beene advanced to a very high Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the State, which Relation he thus cloſeth up; <hi>Cujus generis exempla idcirco proferenda ſunt, ut de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreatur a vectigalibus Regiis, &amp; Civilibus publiciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que occupationibus Clerus, &amp; Evangelio propagando praecipue ſtudeat ac incumbat.</hi> And how ever hee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter takes notice of ſomewhat which happened in the beginning of <hi>Henry</hi> 3. wherein he ſeemes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the fidelity of the Clergy to that of the Laity in adminiſtring of Civill Offices, yet he doth it not as allowing the Clergie to be ſo imployed, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ſecretly taxing the Nobility of that time for being ſo unfaithfull to the King and Kingdome, which ſurely is no warrant for the Clergie to ſtep out of their own Calling.</p>
                     <p>It is true that anciently Biſhops have beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to intermeddle in ſome Civil affairs, at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. <hi>Constantine</hi> made a law to that purpoſe, in caſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156961:4"/> of voluntary appeals from civil Iudicatories, <hi>Sozom.</hi> li. 1. cap. 9. And <hi>Valens</hi> added to it, in caſes of Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals and Schooles. <hi>Hist. Counc. of Trent.</hi> Yet the miſchiefs of ſuch intermedling, were ſoone felt and groaned under. Hence <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Arcadius</hi> made a Law againſt it, and <hi>Valentinian</hi> afterwards put it in execution even in Rome it ſelfe. So did other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, as appeares by the <hi>Corps</hi> of the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> in many places. Indeed ſome ſucceeding Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, gave relaxations, and inlarged the power and preheminence of Biſhops ſo farre, that at length there was no reducing them to their ancient limits, till that once glorious Scepter was become ſo inglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious as to be wholly at the devotion, command, and diſpoſe of the Mitre, to the perpetual ignominie, and irreparable undoing of that puiſſant Empire.</p>
                     <p>And whereas ſome urge that Statute <hi>De Proviſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus</hi> in 25. <hi>Edward</hi> 3. for Biſhops intermedling in Civill Affaires, becauſe it is there ſaid, <q rend="inline">That the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church of England was founded in the eſtate of Prelacy within the Realme of England, by the Kings Anceſtors, and other of the Nobility, to inform them and the People of the Law of God, and to make hoſpitalities, almes, and other works of Charity in the places where the Churches were founded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and for this end, their Lands, revenues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were aſſigned by the ſaid founders to the Prelates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the ſaid Kings in times paſt, were wont to have the greateſt part of their Councel, for the ſafeguard of the Realme, when they had need, of ſuch Prelates, and Clerks ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q> This laſt Clauſe doth only prove <hi>de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> that ſo it was uſed; but doth not legitimate the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156961:5"/> uſe; all ſtories of thoſe times being full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt the miſchiefes which aroſe out of it. And that very Statute declares the prime end of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the Clergy into an Hierarchy, was to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the Kings and others in the Law of God, not in Civill and Martiall matters. And ſo far is ſuch inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling <hi>in Secularibus,</hi> from being countenanced by the Lawes of this Kingdome, that by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law; (which is the moſt fundamentall Law of the Realme) all in holy Orders are ſo carefully exempted from ſuch incumbrances, that if any Clergy man happen to be put into a temporall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, he muſt, upon the pleading of his Orders, have a Writ awarded him out of the Chauncery to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge him. <hi>Regiſt.</hi> 187.6.</p>
                     <p>Therefore it was farre from the intention of the firſt Founders of our Hierarchie, to imploy them in <hi>Civilibus,</hi> but only to make uſe of their counſell in Spirituals.</p>
                     <p>There is yet one thing more, much inſiſted upon by ſome of the Prelates, to prove the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of their intermedling in Secular Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And it is a paſſage of Saint <hi>Auguſtine, De opere Monachor. Cap.</hi> 29. where hee ſaith, It were farre more profitable for him to ſpend his time in reading and praying, <hi>Quàm tumultuoſiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas perplexitates cauſarum alienarum pati de negotiis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularibus, vel judicando dirimendis, vel interveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo praecidendis;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.</note> 
                        <hi>quibus nos moleſtiis idem afflixit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolus, non utique ſuo, ſed ejus qui in eo loquebatur arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio. Ergo,</hi> ſay ſome Biſhops, they have warrant ſo to doe, yea a command from the Apoſtle, and from the Spirit of God himſelfe.</p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:156961:5"/>
                     <p>To this it may be anſwered. 1. That in that very place St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth bemoane this, as being <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiarum quibus ſervit conſuetudo</hi> the cuſtome of thoſe Churches: and the practice began, after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> made a law to warrant it; for S <hi>Auſt.</hi> there ſaith that <hi>Paul</hi> never ſubmitted to it, nay rather he gave order to make them Iudges that were meaneſt, and had leaſt to doe. And albeit St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> there addes that this toyle he undertooke, <hi>non ſine conſolatione Domini in ſpe vitae aeternae, ut fructum feramus cum tolerantia.</hi> Yet this was not ſpoken, as rejoycing in the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but as bearing it with more cheerefulneſſe in hope of eternall life after it. 2. As for the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelfe, he complaines, <hi>violenter irruptum eſt, &amp; non permitter ad quod volo vacare ante meridiem, poſt meridiem occupationibus hominum teneor. Epiſt.</hi> 110.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Poſsidon.</hi> in vit. <hi>Augustini</hi> ca. 19.</note> and <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> that lived with him many yeares, beares him witnes that <hi>hanc ſuam a melioribus rebus occupationem, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> angariam deputabat.</hi> Therefore it was, that (in <hi>Ep.</hi> 110.) he deſired the people that they would ſuffer him to put over all thoſe buſineſſes to <hi>Eradius</hi> whom he had choſen to be his ſucceſſor in his Biſhoprick, which when the people had granted, the good old Father preſently unburdened himſelfe, <hi>Ergo fratres quicquid eſt quod ad me perferebatur, ad illum perferatur, ubi neceſſarium habuerit conſilium, meum non negabo auxilium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. If this be not enough, let me anſwer Biſhops,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Treat.</hi> Of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Subjection and Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Rebellion. <hi>par. 3.</hi>
                        </note> by a Biſhop, <hi>viz:</hi> by Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> who, being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with that place of Saint <hi>Auſtin, de opere Mon:</hi> by the Popiſh crue under the name of <hi>Philander</hi> a <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> returnes this anſwer under the veile of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus</hi> an Orthodoxe Divine; a Truth it is, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156961:6"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:156961:6"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:156961:7"/> Biſhops of the Primitive Church were greatly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with thoſe matters,<note n="*" place="margin">And I have ſhewed before upon what oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. <hi>Prefat.</hi> in <hi>Dial.</hi>
                        </note> not as ordinary <hi>Iudges</hi> of theſe cauſes, but as Arbiters elected by conſent of both parties. <q rend="inline">And I could requite you with <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories</hi> own words of the ſame matter in the ſame place, <hi>quod certum est nos non debere, which it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine we ought not to doe.</hi> But yet I thinke ſo long as it did not hinder their Vocation and Function, though it were troubleſome unto them, they might neither in charity nor in duty refuſe it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it tended to the preſerving of peace and love amongſt men. And the Apoſtle had licenſed all men to chooſe whom they would for their <hi>Iudges,</hi> no doubt meaning that they which were choſen ſhould take the paines to heare the cauſe, and make an end of the ſtrife. But it is one thing to make peace betweene brethren, as they did, by hearing their griefes with conſent of both ſides; and another to claime a judiciall intereſt in thoſe cauſes, in ſpite of mens hearts.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus he, and how home this comes to our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, that will needs ſtill conteſt and ſtrugle to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their Votes in Parliament in all civill cauſes whatſoever, undervaluing all the Reaſons of the Houſe of Commons, and contrary to the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the whole body of the Kingdome, I need not uſe more words to declare.</p>
                     <p>To finiſh this point. All that hath beene ſaid againſt the Clergies intermedling with Civill and Temporall affaires (other than for neceſſary and comfortable proviſions for Lively hood) drives to this Concluſion, that if it be ſo great an hinderance to the exerciſe of the Miniſterial Function to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156961:7"/> in temporall matters which are but ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, it muſt needs be a farre greater hinderance to that holy calling, for Biſhops to Vote in Parliament, becauſe they cannot doe it as it ought to bee done, without ſo much skill and dexterity in ſecular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of all ſorts that poſſibly can come within the debate and reſolution of a Parliament, as muſt needs take up the greateſt part, if not the whole of a mans time, ſtudy, ſtrength and abilities bee they never ſo great and many, to fit him for that great ſervice altogether beſide (I might adde inconſiſtent with) his Calling of the Miniſtery.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>2. ANSWER to the firſt REASON.</head>
                  <q>It is propter majus bonum Eccleſiae.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cujus contrarium, &amp;c.</hi> What good they have done in Parliament, for the Church (unleſſe to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Synagogue of Rome,) let all Hiſtories ſpeake, that have taken any notice of the acting and carriage of matters of Religion debated, and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Parliament, ſince the firſt entrance upon a Reformation in this Kingdome.</p>
                     <p>It is true that in the Reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, one <hi>Cranmer</hi> was active in the cauſe of God, againſt thoſe ſixe bloudy Articles, which coſt ſo many their lives. But, of all the Hierarchie, not one was found to joyne with him, but all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and he alone for three dayes together was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156961:8"/> faine to ſtand to it, and at length, by the malice, practice, and potency of the Prelates, hee was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, and the cauſe carryed againſt him, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments par.</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 1037. <hi>edit.</hi> 1610. This was in the yeare 1540.</p>
                     <p>When about foure or five yeares after, <hi>Cranmer,</hi> in two ſeverall Parliaments uſed his beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to get that bloudy Law repealed, and had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand (as he thought) drawne over to his ſide the Biſhops of <hi>Worceſter, Chicheſter,</hi> and <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> who promiſed to aſſiſt the cauſe in Parliament; yet when it came to the tryall, all the Biſhops forſooke him and the cauſe againe. In ſo much as the King himſelfe, and the Nobility ſtood to him ſo farre, as to give way to a moderating of the former Law, when the Biſhops would not abate the leaſt part of the rigour thereof. <hi>Antiq. Britanni.</hi> in <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his Reigne, it is true, a bleſſed Reformation was happily begun; but, by whom? By the Biſhops? No verily, <hi>Cranmer</hi> only excepted. For he and the Protector were the men that adviſed the King, and went through with the worke. As for the great Biſhops, <hi>Gardiner</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and <hi>Tonſtall</hi> of <hi>Dureſme, Bonner</hi> and others, they ſerved to fill priſons, and diverſe ran away. And in all Letters of the Lords for more particular Reformation, it was onely Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and the Nobilitie that did promote the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. See <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth.</p>
                     <p>But in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, who but Biſhops for the Maſſe, and all the groſſe body of Popery,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156961:8"/> both in Convocation and Parliament? <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and the reſt of the Orthodox Biſhops were ſoone perſecuted, and at length committed to the fire; while the Popiſh Prelates, being reſtored to their places, ſpared no diligence to promote Popiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry throughout the Kingdome, and that by their Votes in Parliament, whereby they might more plentifully ſhed bloud by a Law.</p>
                     <p>When GOD delivered this Kingdome from thoſe <hi>Marian</hi> flames, and ſet up bleſſed Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it cannot be denyed, but that in the Bill for reſtoring all ancient Juriſdictions to the Crown and for reeſtabliſhment of Religion and ejection of Popery, the <hi>Lords Spirituall</hi> are named in the Act, becauſe the bill being carryed by the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Votes, the diſſenting party which was the leſſe, are included in the reſt, and it becomes the Act of all, in common repute, and eſteeme of Law.</p>
                     <p>But little thankes to the Biſhops for any of that Reformation which was then reſtored. We finde the Biſhops of <hi>Wincheſter, Litchfeild, Cheſter, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile</hi> and <hi>Lincolne</hi> appearing in open defence of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery while that Parliament was ſitting. <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Monuments par.</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 1619. <hi>edit.</hi> 1610. But theſe were not all that ſtood for that cauſe: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the deprivation of <hi>Heath Arch-Biſhop of Yorke, Tunſtall Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Durham. White</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter, Thyrlby</hi> of <hi>Ely, Watſon</hi> of <hi>Lincolne, Baines</hi> of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry</hi> and <hi>Litchfeild, Bourne</hi> of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells, Christopherſon</hi> of <hi>Chicheſter, Oglethorp</hi> of <hi>Carlile, Scot</hi> of <hi>Cheſter, Morgan</hi> of Saint <hi>Davids,</hi> beſide <hi>Bonner</hi> impriſoned, <hi>Pates</hi> of <hi>Worceſter, Goldwel</hi> of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156961:9"/> Saint <hi>Aſaph</hi> in exile, for the ſame Pſeudo-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſe. None of all which can with any probability of reaſon bee imagined to have Voted for the reſtoring of the Truth, they being by vertue of that Statute deprived for oppoſing the Truth.</p>
                     <p>And albeit, I know nothing but by heare-ſay of the generall carriage of Biſhops in Parliaments ſithence, and ſo doe not charge them: yet how often they have with-ſtood bills againſt Non-reſidency,<note n="*" place="margin">In 31. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> a Bill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents</hi> paſſed the Houſe of Commons, &amp; being in the other Houſe greatly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of &amp; much ſpoken for by many of the Temporall LORDS, yet, through the earneſt labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, it could have 10 paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage there. Another Bill for reforming Eccleſiaſticall Courts in King <hi>James</hi> his time, paſſed, till it fell among the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and there was ſtayed.</note> Pluralities, and other evils and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in the Reformation of Religion, and of their Courts, the world hath beene ſufficiently infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; inſomuch as the Houſe of Commons hath already declared and reſolved at a Generall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the whole Houſe, <hi>Iune</hi> eleventh, 1641. That the Biſhops have beene found by long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to bee great hinderances of a perfect Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and of the growth of Religion. <hi>En majus bonum Eccleſiae</hi> produced by the Vote of Biſhops in Parliaments!</p>
                     <p>And as their voting in Parliament, in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> is <hi>ad detrimentum, potius quam ad uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem Eccleſiae;</hi> ſo it cannot bee imagined how their Votes there, in <hi>Civilibus,</hi> ſhould conduce more <hi>ad majus bonum Eccleſiae:</hi> Except the wilfull and incorrigible continuing in a courſe forraine and contrary to their proper Calling, and ſuch as (being duely performed) <hi>is a very great hinderance to the exerciſe of their Miniſteriall Function</hi> (as hath beene before declared) can redound to the greater good of the Church, which they ſeldome looke after, unleſſe to receive the profits of it, and to plague
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156961:9"/> thoſe who are profitable in it, that themſelves may more ſplendidly and ſecurely (in Parliament; and every where elſe,) <hi>Lord it over the</hi> whole <hi>heritage of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <head>3. ANSVVER, to the firſt REASON.</head>
                  <q>The Apostles unneceſſarily put themſelves to more hinderances, to worke for their liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, Acts <hi>20.24. 1</hi> Theſſalo. <hi>2.9. 2</hi> Theſſ. <hi>3.8.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vnneceſſarily?</hi> Boldly ſpoken: and were I ſure that one of my fellowes or equalls had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it, I ſhould without breach of good manners, pronounce it ſaucineſſe little ſhort of blaſphemie. Was it not <hi>neceſſary</hi> that the Apoſtles ſhould have a livelihood? And was the procuring of it by <hi>labouring with their hands</hi> (although I know none but one, after CHRISTS Aſcenſion, that was put unto it) to avoyd the oppreſſion of poore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, or to prevent ſcandall among either poore or rich, converted or unconverted, an <hi>unneceſſary</hi> thing? This may bee a ſtraine of Policie paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable enough among Spirituall Lords of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but was never knowne to bee good Divinity
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156961:10"/> among ſuch as deſire to approve themſelves unto GOD.</p>
                     <p>I have bin taught that <hi>Neceſſarium</hi> is put ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>pro utili &amp; pro congruo &amp; convenienti,</hi> as well as <hi>pro naturali ſeu debito,</hi> or <hi>pro violento ſua coacto.</hi> And I have learned among the Schoole-men, that there is a neceſſitie not only <hi>abſolutè &amp; ſimplicite ſic dicta,</hi> but alſo <hi>ex ſuppoſitione &amp; conditione,</hi> when a thing not ſimply neceſſary in it ſelfe, becomes ſuch in regard either of end, meanes, circumſtances <hi>or otherwiſe.</hi> When Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> (1 Epiſt. 2.27. tells the Chriſtians, <hi>yee need not that any man teach you,</hi> was his writing to them to inſtruct them further, <hi>unneceſſary?</hi> When Saint <hi>Pauls abiding in the fleſh</hi> was <hi>more needfull in regard</hi> of the <hi>Philippians, for their furtherance and joy of faith, Philip.</hi> 2. Shall any man be ſo hardy, as to avouch his abode in the fleſh to be unneceſſary, which yet was not ſimply neceſſary in it ſelfe, or unto him?</p>
                     <p>So, circumſtances of time, place, and perſon, may make that <hi>neceſſary</hi> in ſome places, at ſome times, and among ſome perſons, which yet of it ſelfe is not ſo. Thus was it in ſome of thoſe particulars which are called <hi>theſe neceſſary things, Acts</hi> 15.28. yet were it no ſmall preſumption for any man to call <hi>thoſe things,</hi> in reference to that very Text, without ſome diſtinction expreſſed, <hi>unneceſſary.</hi> So it is here.</p>
                     <p>When Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>theſe hands have mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto my neceſsities, Acts</hi> 20.34. ſhal any man ſay, that miniſtration was <hi>unneceſſary?</hi> If it bee ſaid, it was ſo, in regard of his right to maintenance; it is true; but, when it is pronounced without ſuch
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156961:10"/> limitation, it is a contradicting and thwarting of the Apoſtles expreſſion, as if hee wanted skill or care to expreſſe himſelfe as became him, and a miſleading of an uncautious Reader, to ſwallow downe an errour inferred from it. For what is hence intended to bee inferred, but this; That, as the Apoſtles did <hi>unneceſſarily</hi> labour with their hands when they might have avoided it: So Biſhops may according to that example, vote in Parliament, although the thing bee found unneceſſary to a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop? Now this is a corrupt-inference from ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous premiſſes, and the ambiguity lies in the word <hi>unneceſſarily:</hi> for if the word bee ſpoken abſolutely and without all limitation, it is abſolutely falſe: if a limitation bee intended, it ought to have been expreſſed, and then any intelligent Reader would ſoone have beene led to conſider and compare that act of the Apoſtle, with the preſent <hi>unneceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of Biſhops votes in Parliaments; and thereby have beene enabled to diſcover the weakneſſe and unſufficiency of this unneceſſary impertinent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, becauſe hee would eaſily have found great and wide differences betweene thoſe two caſes. 1. Working for a livelihood is a matter of neceſſity, when it cannot otherwiſe bee ſo well obtained without oppreſſion or ſcandall, which was the Apoſtles caſe: But Biſhops voting in Parliament, when no neceſſity at all, either of maintenance or ſcandall can bee feared, is a worke of ſupererroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and an unneceſſary ſinfull neglect of their owne Function. 2. The Apoſtles working with his hands might better conſiſt with the exerciſe of his Miniſteriall Office,<note place="margin">Mat 10.19, 20 Ioh. 16.13, 14</note> becauſe hee had his furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156961:11"/> thereunto by divine inſpiration,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.11, 12.</note> whereas all men now muſt continually and induſtriouſly apply themſelves to their Bookes and Meditations, to make them <hi>workemen that need not to bee aſhamed.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.13. 2 Tim. 2.15.</note> 3. The Apoſtles working with his hands was but for a ſeaſon while the preſent neceſſity laſted, but the Biſhops would willingly Vote in Parliament to the end of the world, although there bee no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of it at all, but great inconvenience and ſcandall accruing to the Church thereby, and a Bil tranſmitted by the honourable Houſe of Commons to the Lords againſt it, as many wayes inconvenient and intolerable.</p>
                     <p>It were eaſie to adde more differences, but theſe may ſuffice: So alſo may that which hath beene already ſaid,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.9. 2 Theſ. 3.8.</note> for the clearing of thoſe other two Texts that remaine.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="answer">
                  <head>4. ANSVVER, to the firſt REASON.</head>
                  <q>What hinderance can it be to their Calling, that once in three yeares, when they muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend the Convocation, they divide ſome part of that ſhort time to the attendance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>This is not an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> but a Queſtion; and ſuch as, if the firſt <hi>Anſwer</hi> bee true, little needed. But that which hath beene ſaid in examination of that firſt Anſwere, may alſo ſuffice to ſatisfie this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156961:11"/> Interrogation. The <hi>hinderance</hi> lyes not ſo much in the expence of a ſhort ſpace ſpent in the Parliament Houſe, as in the long time requiſite to fit a Biſhop for ſuch multiplicity of weighty buſineſſes as are proper for a Parliament: except hee thinke it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to vote Bils by rote, according to the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe of his friends, or the loudneſſe of the cryes made for or againſt them.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, Times and other Circumſtances may, and often do ſo alter the State of the ſame matters; that, if even the ableſt and moſt vigilant Sateſman bee not more aware, Bils may be offered, which are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps moſt plauſible in preſent appearance, and might bee very profitable too, at ſome other ſeaſon, that would prove moſt pernicious in the iſſue, if now they were ſuffered to paſſe. Now, he that hath not his eyes in his head, or his head not conſtantly at worke (even out of Parliament) to obſerve and ponder the ſeverall changes and windings of affairs and ſeaſons, can never bee a judicious Peere in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; but (at his beſt) an Emperick, who, when his totall is caſt up, is ever found more hurtfull than profitable, yea a very peſt to the publike; unleſſe, laying all other buſineſſe aſide, hee double his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry to make future recompence for his preſent inſufficiency, and by his diligence to ſupply the defects of his former education, as to this Calling, he having been firſt intended and moulded for another profeſſion.</p>
                     <p>And, if Biſhops take this courſe,<note place="margin">1 Chro. 12.32</note> to become like <hi>the children of Iſsachar, men that have underſtanding of the times to know what Iſrael ought to doe,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able themſelves for Parliaments indeed; it is eaſie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156961:12"/> to conclude, what hinderance this not onely may bee, but cannot but bee to their Miniſteriall Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For, if the <hi>Levite</hi> take upon him <hi>Iſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chars</hi> Office, and fall to tampering ſo high in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.14.</note> hee will ſoone prove an <hi>Iſſachar</hi> in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, and become couchant betweene his two bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</p>
                     <p>Againe, I hope it will very ſhortly appeare, that it will be farre from being <hi>neceſſary</hi> for Biſhops <hi>once in three yeares, to attend the Convocation,</hi> as the frame of both yet ſtandeth among us. Our <hi>Convocation</hi> is but a meere ſhadow, a plaine mockery. Synods were ordained for more uſe and activity, than to patter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a latine Let any upon Wedneſdays and Fridays, and to give ſo many Subſidies as it pleaſeth his Grace to propound to the engaged and enthralled Clergy; or to paſſe a few illegall, ſeditious, Anti-parliamentary Canons, firſt caſt in the mould of ſome brain ſick Incendiary, that would needs be the <hi>Dominus fac totum,</hi> and the head of a pragmaticall, Papiſticall, Atheiſticall Sanction.</p>
                     <p>And, if Synods were (as I truſt they wil bee) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their priſtine courſe and extent, agreeable to the Word (without which, better we never ſaw Convocation more; as, I hope, wee ſhall not) there would be ſo much worke to doe in them, as would even tire out the moſt indefatigable ſpirits of the ableſt men, to conſider of errours in doctrine which daily creepe in to corrupt the truth; of explanations of Doctrine already eſtabliſhed, when perverſe men make uſe of the generality or ambiguity of the terms wherein they bee couched, to countenance their fancies and fanaticke opinions; of preparing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156961:12"/> platforme of Diſcipline agreeable to the will of God, and uſefull for his people; of cenſuring ſuch as bee too great for leſſer Aſſemblies; and of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales from inferiour Synods to that higher Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorie.</p>
                     <p>Then, would godly and conſcientious Biſhops finde ſo much to doe in Convocations or Synods, as would leave them little leaſure for attendance in Parliaments, where the Peeres doe, or ſhould ſit every day (or they have little reaſon to Vote in thoſe Bills and Cauſes there agitated, when they have not heard the debates;) and ſoone let them ſee, that all the time they could redeeme (although they ſate every day, and ſate out the day) would bee much too little maturely to diſcuſſe, and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to determine all buſineſſes of Synods. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it muſt needs bee a <hi>very great hinderance</hi> to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per worke of their Calling, when, <hi>once in three yeares they muſt neceſſarily attend the Convocation</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and reſtored to the truly Primitive nature, and uſe) if <hi>they divide</hi> any <hi>part of that ſhort time to the</hi> attendance of Parliament. Thus farre the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of all the <hi>Anſwers,</hi> to the firſt <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which being the Principall, I have beene the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in it, aſwell for the aſſerting of the <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelfe, as for examining the ſtrength of the <hi>Anſwers</hi> that would, but cannot enervate or abate the vigour of it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reason">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:156961:13"/>
               <head>II. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they doe vow and undertake it at their Ordination, when they enter into holy Orders, that they will give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholely to that Vocation.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>I. ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>This Vow and undertaking in Miniſters Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination is quite miſtaken: The words are in the Biſhops Exhortation, not in the Miniſters Anſwer.<note place="margin">To this a three fold <hi>Anſwer</hi> is given.</note>
                  </q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mistaken,</hi> and <hi>quite miſtaken?</hi> Why ſo? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the words are in the Biſhops Exhortation, not in the Miniſters Anſwer.</hi> But where hath the Houſe of Commons yet ſaid, that the <hi>words are in the Miniſters Anſwer?</hi> Surely not in their ſecond <hi>Reaſon,</hi> againſt which this <hi>Anſwer</hi> is directed. Therefore, this branch of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to that <hi>Reaſon</hi> might have well beene ſpared.</p>
                     <p>The words are confeſſed by the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> to bee uſed at the <hi>Miniſters Ordination.</hi> This is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to juſtifie the Houſe of Commons, and their <hi>Reaſon.</hi> And, what though it bee ſpoken by the Biſhop, not by the Miniſter at that time? this doth not diſprove his <hi>Vow.</hi> Little children utter no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156961:13"/> words in Baptiſme; yet, doe they not enter into a <hi>Vow,</hi> when the Miniſter declareth upon what terms they be admitted, and the whole action is managed by others?</p>
                     <p>The Biſhop ſpeakes theſe words at the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Miniſters; <hi>We have a good hope that you have well weighed and pondered theſe things with your ſelves, long before this time, and that you have clearely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by Gods Grace, to give your ſelves wholly to this Vocation, whereunto it hath pleaſed God to call you, ſo that (as much as lyeth in you) you apply your ſelves whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this one thing, and draw all your cares and ſtudies this way, and to this end.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All this the Miniſters heare when they enter into holy Orders. The Biſhop takes it for granted that they have done all this; that they have ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved, and <hi>decreed</hi> it, (as the Latine hath it) long before, and that by invocating of Gods Grace for performance; which decree before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, with invocation ſuppoſed, and conſent at preſent to bee admitted into Holy Orders upon this condition, by their ſilence witneſſed, makes it to amount (materially, if not formally, <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad omnia</hi>) to a Vow, that is, to ſuch an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as engageth them to <hi>undertake</hi> and make good what in this Reaſon is affirmed of them. For, I have learned ſo much out of <hi>Calvin,</hi> the Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, that ſometimes <hi>Votum ponitur pro conſenſu.</hi> and no man denies ſilence, in ſuch an action,<note place="margin">Lexic. Incid.</note> to bee conſent. And more than this, the Houſe of Commons ſay not: for they ſpeake not of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Vow vocally pronounced by the Miniſter, in that action.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:156961:14"/>
                     <p>Howbeit, if I may utter my private opinion freely of this point, without prejudice to the Houſe of Commons, and without engaging them further than themſelves intended, I humbly conceive, that the Church of England, in her fifth Queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the Biſhop in the ordering of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, doth fully intend as much as is contained in thoſe words of the Exhortation before rehearſed: and, to that Queſtion, the Miniſter poſitively anſwereth, <hi>I will endeavour my ſelfe ſo to doe, the Lord being my helper. Ergo,</hi> hee formally voweth at his Ordination, what is contained in the Second Reaſon of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
                     <p>To cleare this, I ſhall firſt ſet downe the words of the Queſtion; <hi>Will you bee diligent in prayers, and in reading of the holy Scriptures, and in ſuch ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as helpe to the knowledge of the ſame, laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Study of the World and the Fleſh?</hi> To this, the party to bee ordained anſwereth, <hi>I Will endeavour my ſelfe ſo to doe, the Lord being my helper.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Next, I muſt pray the Readers to conſider, that the ſureſt expoſition of theſe words muſt needs bee found in that Booke from whence the words were taken, and ſet into the Booke of Ordination more briefly than in the Originall they bee expreſſed. All the learned know, that <hi>Bucer</hi> was the chief man, who at the requeſt of <hi>Cranmer,</hi> cenſured the firſt Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Leiturgie of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. whereupon it was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a better forme.</p>
                     <p>In that firſt Booke, there was no forme of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> preſcribed: but in the 5. 6. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156961:14"/> was added. This <hi>Exhortation</hi> and the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Anſwers</hi> to them, in our preſent Booke of <hi>Ordination,</hi> were not borrowed (as ſome ſuggeſt) out of the Romane Pontificall, but were <hi>Verbatim</hi> taken out of that grave and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Treatiſe of <hi>Bucer</hi> entituled, <hi>De Ordinat. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitima Miniſtrorum Eccleſ. Cap. ult.</hi> extant in his <hi>Script. Anglican. Ergo,</hi> the full meaning and latitude of this Queſtion muſt bee taken thence.</p>
                     <p>Now the Queſtion is there propounded thus; <hi>Tempus omne quod vobis a ſacris Miniſteriis publicis &amp; privatis, ac neceſſaria &amp; frugali cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris cura ſuperfuerit, id omne precibus &amp; lectione Divinarum Scripturarum, iiſque ſtudiis quae cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Scripturarum, &amp; docendi facultatem adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant &amp; ornant, rejectis a vobis cunctis mundi &amp; carnis studiis &amp; negotiis, feriis &amp; ludicris, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendetis?</hi> The Anſwere, <hi>Impendemus, juvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te nos Domino.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So then, the full latitude of the Queſtion (which is contracted in the booke of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) extends to a ſolemne vow and undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Miniſters part, when hee enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Holy Orders, to beſtow all his time, either in the exerciſe of his Office, or fitting himſelfe further for it; and, to lay aſide not onely the <hi>vanities</hi> and <hi>pomps</hi> of this wicked world (as hee vowed to doe in Baptiſme;) but all ſecular <hi>buſineſses</hi> and imployments; neceſſary proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for himſelfe and family (which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe impoſeth upon all) excepted. And all this,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156961:15"/> in his ſolemne <hi>Anſwere</hi> made to the Biſhop at his Ordination, the Miniſter formally covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and voweth by Gods grace to performe. Which being ſo, there can no ſcruple remaine in any impartiall man, but that the ſecond <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the Houſe of Commons is true, ſolid, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding againſt the Biſhops Votes in Parliament, <hi>quod erat demonstrandum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>2. ANS. to the ſecond REASON.</head>
                  <q>The Biſhop hopes they will give themſelves wholely to that, and not to any other Trade or Vocation.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>And <hi>hope</hi> ſo hee cannot, if Biſhops may ſtill vote in Parliament. Becauſe they cannot doe that, with profit or ſafety to the Common wealth, without giving their mindes not to ſome one other ſingle trade or vocation only, but to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very trade and courſe of life, ſo farre as to make them complete Sateſmen, as hath beene ſhewed before. For, what Trade or Vocation is there to be found, which ſometime or other makes not buſineſſe for the Parliament? And how ſhall hee give a Vote in it with judgement, that hath not a good inſight into all the Myſteries of it.</p>
                     <p>If it ſhould (as poſſibly it may) bee objected,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156961:15"/> that by this ſtrict rule, many of the Nobility, ſhould bee excluded? I anſwere, that if they bee not throughly qualified and furniſhed for that worke, the more the pity, becauſe the more the Common wealth ſuffers by their inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency. Howbeit the ingenuouſneſſe of their nature and education, will make them leſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in ſpeaking, and more diligent in hearing their ancients and men of more gravitie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Nor is it fit that for ſuch inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies they ſhould be turned out, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine there as in a Schoole (as wee ſee ſome of the ſonnes of the Noblemen doe) to traine them up to doe ſervice there to the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it being an honour to which they were borne; whereas Biſhops ſit there but <hi>Precario,</hi> and are out of their Callings all the while.</p>
                     <p>But, is that all that the Biſhop <hi>hopes,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the perſons to bee ordained will not take <hi>another Trade or Vocation</hi> upon them? Then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, if a Miniſter doe not profeſſe the Trade of a Taylor, hee may yet ſpend part of his time in Tayloring. Hee may ſometimes give himſelf to Brewing, ſo he ſet not up a Brewhouſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſurely our Law is ſo ſtrict in ſuch caſes, that it forbids Miniſters to have ſo much as a Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe or Tan-houſe, although managed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, further than for the neceſſaries of houſe keeping; nor otherwiſe, to take to Farme or Leaſe, any Lands or Tenements, albeit the ſame bee occupied by ſome other perſons,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156961:16"/> if it bee to the Miniſters uſe. 21. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8 13.</p>
                     <p>And why ſo? Is it becauſe the Lawes doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie the wealth of Spirituall perſons? That were an uncharitable ſurmiſe. The end was, that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters might have no occaſions of a vocation from their Studies and Miniſteriall Function, but have more opportunity to beſtow themſelves wholely thereupon, according to what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and undertooke at their Ordination, <hi>for the more quiet and vertuous increaſe and maintenance of Divine Service, and preaching and teaching of the Word of God, &amp;c.</hi> as the entrance into that Statute doth expreſſe it.</p>
                     <p>So then, if we conſider Biſhops, according to what the Common wealth expecteth from them in her Lawes, as well as what the Church bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them unto in their Ordination, as Miniſters of the Church of England, they may not regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, give themſelves not onely wholly to any Trade, but not at all to any imployment but the Miniſtery, and to that which is neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to fit them for it, and ſupport them in it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <head>3. ANS. to the ſecond REASON.</head>
                  <q>Wholely in a Morall, and not in a Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſenſe, that will admit no Latitude: els there might the ſame exception bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their juſt care of proviſion for their houſhold affaires.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:156961:16"/>
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>If they by their Ordination bee bounded Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; the Houſe of Commons will never, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, trouble themſelves about the <hi>Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cality</hi> of the <hi>Vow.</hi> Nor will I be ſo bold, to ſay of this diſtinction, of the words of the <hi>Exhortation</hi> in queſtion, as the Author of the <hi>Holy Table, Name, and Thing,</hi> doth of a like ſubtile interpretation of a <hi>Rubrick,</hi> newly minted by his Antagoniſt, <hi>praying him to remember,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Page. 54.</note> 
                        <hi>that the Rubrick was written for the uſe of the Engliſh, not of the Gypſies or Egyptians.</hi> Yet this I ſuppoſe I may freely and truly ſay, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Learned and Pious <hi>Martin Bucer,</hi> nor the plaine meaning Church of England, which borrowed that Exhortation from <hi>Bucer,</hi> ever ſo much as dreamt of the Mathematickes, or of that diſtinction here given, in thoſe words of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; but meant honeſtly and plainly to let all Miniſters know, that, without diſtinctions or tricks, they are to bind themſelves wholly and abſolutely, <hi>Mathematically</hi> aſwell as <hi>Morally,</hi> to that Vocation of the Miniſtery; further than the neceſſity of livelyhood enforceth them to ſpend ſome time to ſupply the wants and neceſſary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of them and theirs. And to this I may, I hope, without offence make bold to adde (becauſe I have learnt it from the ſame Author, of the <hi>Holy Table, &amp;c.</hi> page 52. as hee out of <hi>Aristotle, Anal. Poſt. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 12) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>You muſt not diſpute in termes of Geometry; with thoſe that verſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156961:17"/> not in Geometry; otherwiſe you will ſhew your ſelfe but a foule and ſophiſticall diſputant,</hi> as that Author hath it.</p>
                     <p>But let the diſtinction bee as it will; thus much is clearely gotten by it, that the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by yeeldeth, that, <hi>Morally</hi> Biſhops cannot vote in Parliament, without croſſing the expectation of, and condition propounded by the Church, in admitting them to Holy Orders; and that they vote there and imploy themſelves in ſecular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires <hi>Mathematically</hi> only. Surely, if their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there (for that wee know is the thing to bee aſſerted by him in his <hi>Anſwers,</hi> becauſe that is it which is oppoſed in the Reaſons of the Houſe of Commons) conſiſt not with the Rules of Morality, it is no great credit for them to retaine that honour, nor will it at length bring in much comfort to them, when they muſt yeeld up their accounts to God, that they were never forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it according to the ſtrict Lawes of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematickes,</hi> although indeed <hi>Morally</hi> they were bound from it.</p>
                     <p>And what, muſt they needs bee debarred from <hi>the juſt care of proviſion of their houſhold affaires,</hi> if denyed votes in Parliament, and liberty unto ſecular imployments, to enable them ſo to vote? Nay, God himſelfe not only allowes, but impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth upon all men a care of their family-buſineſſe and government, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.23. and he that is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent herein, is pronounced <hi>worſe than an Infidell,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. God hath not divided this from any Calling, in ordinary courſe. And what hee hath
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156961:17"/> joyned, no man may ſeparate. Therefore, both the Church in her <hi>Ordination</hi> (as appeared by the larger expreſſion thereof before out of <hi>Bucer</hi>) and the Kingdome, in her Lawes (as is alſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the Statute before alledged) excepteth this care of proviſion for their houſholds, when yet both Church and Kingdome binde them to give themſelves (in all other particulars) wholly to the Calling, ſtudy and exerciſe of the <hi>Miniſtery, which they have received in the Lord,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Colloſ. 4 17</note> 
                        <hi>that they may fulfill it.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <head>III. REAS. of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe Councels and Canons in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ages do forbid them to meddle with Secular Affaires.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>I. ANSVVER.<note place="margin">To this 3. <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> a five fold <hi>Anſwere</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</note>
                  </head>
                  <q>Councels and Canons against Biſhops Votes in Parliament, were never in uſe in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and therefore they are aboliſhed by the Statute, <hi>of 25. Hen. 8.</hi>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>II. ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>So are they by the ſame Statute, becauſe the Lords have declared that the Biſhops vote hereby the Lawes and Statutes of this Realm; and all Canons that croſſe with thoſe, are there aboliſhed.</q>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:156961:18"/>
                  <head>III. ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>So are they by the ſame Statute, as thwarting the Kings Prerogative to call Biſhops by ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to vote in Parliament.</q>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="answer">
                  <head>IV. ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>So are they by the Vote of the Houſe of Commons. <hi>21.</hi> Maii <hi>1641.</hi> becauſe they are not confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Act of Parliament.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>I put all theſe <hi>Anſwers</hi> together, becauſe they will not need diſtinct Examinations, they being much what coincident, at leaſt in the maine ſcope, which is; to keepe this third <hi>Reaſon</hi> out of the Court, as being no ſufficient evidence in Law, to eject the Defendants out of their holds in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt ſome of their deſires.</p>
                     <p>It is acknowledged, that no Councels or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, not confirmed by Parliament have, here in England, any power to bind the ſubjects ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Clergie, or of the Laitie; as hath been clearly <hi>Reſolved upon the Queſtion,</hi> this Parliament, in both houſes.</p>
                     <p>But whether the Houſe of Commons referre to any Canons ſo confirmed, I may not take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee to affirme or deny; becauſe they have beene pleaſed to forbeare to cite thoſe to which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156961:18"/> they doe referre. Nor can it bee, I thinke, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that any Canons were in uſe within forty yeares before the Statute of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.19. (to which I conceive the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> hath relation) againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops votes in Parliament: and ſo, Biſhops bee ſhot free from ſuch Canons, if urged againſt them in that capacity, as binding Lawes.</p>
                     <p>But what neede the Anſwerer to have taken all this paines of multiplying of <hi>Anſweres</hi> to ſhew that no Councels or Canons not ratified by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, bee binding to Biſhops, in this or any caſe whatſoever? For, where hath the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſo urged them? Surely, not here. They have not vouched them as Lawes to thruſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops out of the Houſe of Peeres, as ſitting there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lawes already in being; but, as rationall Arguments and prudentiall Grounds, to induce the Parliament to uſe their Legiſlative power to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate the Lawes (if any be) for their ſitting there; ſeeing that many godly Biſhops in former Ages have made divers religious and wholeſome Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and Proviſions againſt ſuch exorbitant uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations of the Clergie. For however thoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons bee not formally obligatory here, yet are they really worthy the Conſideration of thoſe who have a power to reduce Biſhops by a binding Law to that which heretofore ſo many learned and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men of their owne Coat and Calling, have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and decreed to be juſt and neceſſarie.</p>
                     <p>Further than this the Houſe of Commons bee not engaged. And who knows not that the Biſhops and their Officers have, and ſtill doe urge divers Canons of forraigne Councels and domeſtique
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156961:19"/> too, that never were confirmed by Parliament) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both Clergie and Laitie, when ſuch Canons make for the Biſhops or their Officers. And theſe muſt take effect, like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians.</hi> And yet now, when they ſee ſuch Canons tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon themſelves, although not as Lawes, but as rationall arguments only, how witty they be in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off all by the Statute of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. which makes nothing at all againſt the Houſe of Commons, or this <hi>Reaſon</hi> produced by them!</p>
                     <p>And what offence, or incongruity was it in the Houſe of Commons, to urge Canons and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels againſt the Biſhops in this particular, when no Divine that ever complained of ſuch uſurpations of the Clergie hath held it incongruous to preſſe the very ſame againſt them? I will not trouble my ſelfe or others with many inſtances; that alone ſhall ſuffice, which hath beene before<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Exam.</hi> of the firſt <hi>Anſwe</hi> to the firſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> alledged out of <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> Archbiſhop of Canterburie. That Prelate taxing the exceſſive exorbitances, and ſcandalous courſes of the Clergie, in the reigne of <hi>Richard</hi> 1. was not affraid to give this as the chiefe (if not the only) reaſon of all that prodigious break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, <hi>Quod contra Orthodoxorum Patrum decreta &amp;c.</hi> that contrary to the decrees of the Orthodoxe Fathers, the Clergie did too much intermeddle in worldly buſineſſes.</p>
                     <p>If then, ſo great a Prelate did well in laying this home to the charge of the Clergie, that their not regarding the Decrees and Canons of former Councels, was the maine cauſe of all the evills committed by them; it cannot unbecome the Houſe of Commons aſſembled in Parliament, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156961:19"/> a Bill againſt Biſhops Votes in Parliament, to produce and uſe the Canons and Councels, of Biſhops themſelves againſt ſuch courſes, held on and maintained by our Biſhops againſt the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſolemne determinations of their owne Predeceſſors, in the Prelacy in all the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>As for the Declaration of the Lords, that <hi>the Biſhops Vote in Parliament by the Lawes and Statutes of the Realme,</hi> I meddle not with it, becauſe as I am ignorant of the Lawes and Statutes by which they vote, ſo am I not acquainted with what the Lords have declared thereupon. Only I have heard, that divers <hi>Abbots voted as anciently in Parliament as Biſhops, yet are taken away.</hi> Yea, this <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> hath informed mee,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> 7.</note> that anciently the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were <hi>aſsiſted</hi> in Parliament; <hi>with a dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble number of Mitred Abbots and Priors.</hi> But Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> could find no more in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Rolles but twenty ſeven Abbots and two Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, <hi>Commentary</hi> on <hi>Littleton Inſtitutes Sec.</hi> 138. Nor doe I know the difference of the Tenures of the one or of the other; or why in regard of originall right, Biſhops ſhould rather vote in Parliament than <hi>Abbots</hi> and <hi>Priors,</hi> ſo long as thoſe Orders continued in being. That great Maſter of Law, before named tels us, that both Abbots and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were called to Parliament by the Kings <hi>Writ,</hi> elſe, they came not there,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> although they held of the King <hi>Per Baroniam.</hi> Witneſſe the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of the Monaſterie of <hi>Feverſham</hi> founded by King <hi>Stephen,</hi> who albeit hee held by Barony, yet for that hee was not called by Writ hee never
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156961:20"/> ſate in Parliament. And perhaps, it is not ſimply a Barony that gives all the Biſhops a right to fit there, for I have read ſomewhere, that all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. his foundation have not Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronies annexed to them. Yet they are called by Writ, and vote as Peeres in Parliament.</p>
                     <p>But, bee their right what it will, I heare nothing from the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> how farre this right extended. The Lords have, I believe, declared, in this very Parliament, that the Biſhops have no votes <hi>in cauſa Sanguinis;</hi> and, I thinke the Biſhops have found it to be ſo. And to my ignorance it is a ſcruple, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had originally any libertie of Votes in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and State affaires, and were not reſtrained meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to matters of Religion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ibid</note>The reaſon of my ſcruple is, becauſe I finde in the ſame Commentaries of Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> (for I confeſſe, I aſpire not ſo high as to looke into the Rolle it ſelfe) a tranſcript of an ancient Record for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding them to intermeddle,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rol. Pat. de An</hi> 18. H. 3. 1 16 17.</note> upon paine of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Baronies, with any matters concerning the Crowne, the perſon of the King, his Eſtate, or the State of his Councell: the words are theſe; <hi>Mandatum eſt omnibus Epiſcopis qui conventuri ſunt apud Glouceſtriam die Sabbati in Craſtin' Sanctae Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinae, firmiter inhibendo, quod ſicut Baronias ſuas quas de Rege tenent,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Vide Pol. Virg. in <hi>H. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>diligunt, nullo modo praeſumant Concilium tenere de aliquibus quae Coronam Regis pertinent, vel quae Perſonam Regis, vel ſtatum ſuum, vel ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Concilii ſui contingunt; ſcituri pro certo, quod ſi fecerint, Rex inde ſe capiet ad Baronias ſuas. Teſte Rege apud Hereford,</hi> 23. <hi>Novemb. &amp;c.</hi> This was in the 8. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. and, in a great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:156961:20"/> or Parliament;<note place="margin">In Hen. <hi>3</hi> ad an. <hi>1234.</hi>
                        </note> not in a private Councell of Domeſticks of his owne Court, as <hi>Polydore Virgil,</hi> and <hi>Matthew of Westminster</hi> would inſinuate.</p>
                     <p>Touching the <hi>Kings Prerogative,</hi> it is too ſacred to be handled by common or private hands. Farre be it from me to ſet bounds to it, or to wade farre in it. Only, I believe that the Kings Prerogative is for the good of his people: and, if any perſon unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and altogether unfit (and therefore uncapable) ſhould, by the Prerogative Royall, be called to, and imployed in any place or office of truſt, wherein the whole Kingdome is interreſſed, this were an abuſe of the Prerogative, cauſed by Him that did miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the King; and there is no doubt, but a juſt King who ſhould be ſo abuſed, would ſoone upon better information, recall ſuch a Grant, or Writ. If then the Biſhops ſhall be found to be perſons altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit for ſuch high honour and truſt (wherein all the Kingdome is ſo deeply concerned) I only ask (I determine not) what <hi>thwarting of the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> it could juſtly bee ſaid to bee, to paſſe an Act with the Kings <hi>Soit fait, &amp;c.</hi> unto it, that no more ſuch Writs ſhall henceforth iſſue to any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Kingdome.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="answer">
                  <head>5. ANS. to the third REASON.</head>
                  <q>This Argument was in a manner deſerted by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Perpoint,</hi> and confeſt to be but an <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ad hominem.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:156961:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:156961:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:156961:22"/>
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>It is very true, that Noble Gentleman, after he had faithfully and like himſelfe diſcharged the truſt committed to him by the Houſe of Commons in writing, hee added a few words, in the cloſe of that Conference with the Lords to this effect; that how ever hee was commanded to urge this Reaſon taken from <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Canons,</hi> yet the Houſe did only borrow theſe Arrowes out of the Biſhops own Quivers, to uſe them as weapons againſt themſelvs; not with any purpoſe to bind the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons or other the ſubjects by them.</p>
                     <p>This was not in any ſort a deſertion of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but a ſeaſonable explanation of the Houſe of Commons in what ſenſe they uſed it. And were it but <hi>Argumentum ad hominem,</hi> yet was it <hi>ad illos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> whome it chiefly and moſt neerly concerned, to wit the Biſhops themſelvs, and had force enough in my apprehenſion, to ſilence them, if they ſhould offer to open their mouthes in defence of holding their places and votes in Parliament, any longer. For, if they would but conſider what ſo many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Biſhops and Councels have ſaid, and decreed againſt Clergie mens interpoſing in, and mingling themſelves with Civill and Secular affaires (which yet be not of that import and conſequence, as theſe in queſtion bee) common ingenuity would make them to lay their hands upon their mouthes, and leave the diſcuſſion and determination hereof to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are not intereſſed in it, and therfore more likely to bee leſſe partiall in reſolving of it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reason">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:156961:22"/>
               <head>IV. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe the twentie foure Biſhops have a dependency upon the Archbiſhops, and becauſe of their Canonicall obedience to them.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>1. ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>They have no dependency upon the Archbiſhops, but in points of Appeale, and Viſitation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And owe them no obedience,<note place="margin">To this <hi>Reaſon</hi> a two fold <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwe</hi> is framed.</note> but in theſe two points. None at all in Parliament, where they are <hi>pares</hi> their Equals: And, as <hi>Bracton</hi> tels us, <hi>Par in Parem non habet imperium.</hi> What hath Canonicall obedience to doe with a vote in Parliament, declared in this Bill to be no Eccleſiaſticall, but a ſecular affaire?</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Reaſon</hi> conſiſts of two branches, <hi>dependency</hi> and <hi>obedience;</hi> both which render Biſhops unmeet to vote in Parliament. For, where theſe two relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons meet, make but the Archbiſhops of a ſide, and it will be eaſie to draw the reſt the ſame way. The <hi>Anſwer</hi> endeavours to take off both at one pull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is neither <hi>dependance</hi> upon, nor <hi>obedience</hi> due to the Archbiſhops but in two points, <hi>Appeales,</hi> and <hi>Viſitations,</hi> which no way concern Parliaments or the diſpoſe of their votes therein, where they bee all <hi>Equals,</hi> and where the Vote is only a <hi>Secular</hi> Act.</p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:156961:23"/>
                     <p>To examine the truth of the Anſwere ſo farre as it denyes all <hi>dependency</hi> or <hi>obedience,</hi> but in <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales,</hi> and <hi>Viſitations,</hi> were not altogether imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; if it were a time of leaſure, becauſe it is with ſo much confidence denyed. Bee there no reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Caſes pertaining to the Metropolitane, no Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative wills, no Inhibitions that may runne, and command in the Dioceſans Territories and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, ſave onely in Caſes of <hi>Appeales,</hi> and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of Metropoliticall <hi>Viſitations?</hi> Doth not the Archbiſhop command the ſeverall Biſhops, upon divers occaſions, to publiſh divers things, whether decreed in Synodes, or received from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority?</p>
                     <p>Hath the Metropolitan no power to correct and cenſure the delinquencies of the Biſhops of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and to command them, by vertue of their Canonicall Obedience, to be more vigilant and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, when hee findes them ſlacke in their Office; to enjoyne them ſilence and obedience, if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and ruffle with his Grace <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to give other ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and interpretations of Rubricks and other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters contained in the Liturgie, than the Biſhop doth, ſo hee expound nothing contrary to the Booke; and is not the Biſhop to bee concluded by it? It were eaſie to adde many moe particulars, which cannot bee reduced to <hi>Appeales</hi> or <hi>Viſitations.</hi> Therefore here the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> came ſhort in his rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning.</p>
                     <p>But hee that deſires to looke abroad and to ſee more of this, may conſult <hi>Lancelott. Peruſin. Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. Iur. Can. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. <hi>De Epiſcopis &amp; ſummo Pontif. Cap. Ad hos.</hi> in the addition of <hi>Io. Bapt.</hi> where
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:156961:23"/> it is ſaid, <hi>in multiplicibus caſibus Archiepiſcopus in ſubditos Epiſcopos ordinariam habet juriſdictionem, ut in C. paſtoralis de offi. ordin. &amp; Sylveſt. ponit duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cim.</hi> And if theſe be not enow, hee may alſo ſee <hi>Hostienſis ſum. li.</hi> 1. <hi>de offic. ordin.</hi> where there be more caſes (even eighteene in number) expreſſed in certaine verſes, which are there likewiſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by the ſame Author of thoſe ſummes <hi>Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus de Seguſio.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Officium varium, forus, appellatio, crimen</l>
                        <l>Peccans, non parens, res, conſultatio, deſes</l>
                        <l>Praeſul, Canonici tumidi, ſententia nequam.</l>
                        <l>Viſitat, indulget Cuſtos quia Papa dat uſus,</l>
                        <l>Permutat ſocijs ſuſpectum cum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> remittit.</l>
                        <l>Caſibus his Primas<note n="*" place="margin">
                              <hi>Subjectos,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan.</note> ſubjectio Praſules arcet.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>I forbeare to mention our owne <hi>Lindwood,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moe. Theſe may ſuffice to ſhew in how many things Biſhops have dependance upon, and may be obnoxious to their Metropolitan, and how many wayes the Arch-Biſhop can meet with them, if they go not his way in all things that he is ſet upon.</p>
                     <p>And were it true, that there is no <hi>dependency</hi> upon, nor <hi>obedience</hi> due to the Arch-biſhop, but in <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales, and Viſitations,</hi> as it is a truth that theſe have in themſelves no reference to Votes in Parliament: yet, who knowes not what influence an active and pragmaticall Arch-biſhop hath into the Votes of all his Suffragans, whom hee can pleaſure or diſpleaſe as he liſteth, as they Vote with him, or diſſent from him, after intimation or inſinuation of his mind in private to them?</p>
                     <p>Indeed, if we could imagine Biſhops and Arch-Biſhops to be ſo complete in ſincerity and ſanctitie
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:156961:24"/> as their high Calling beſpeakes them, there were little ſtrength in this Reaſon of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. But, as the Prelates bee men, and not free from that which is humane, ſo the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons conceived it not undecent or uncharitable to inſinuate ſomething more than is plainely expreſſed to ſuch an Honourable and Intelligent Aſſembly of Lords: which reaſon as it is, hath force enough in it to weigh with rationall men; however, for the reverence they bare to the Miniſteriall function, the Houſe held it fitter to leave ſomewhat to be tacite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood, than to ſpeake all out that is couched under it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>2. ANSWER to the fourth REASON.</head>
                  <q>This Argument reacheth not the two Arch-Biſhops, diſcharged in the Rubricke from this Oath: and therefore is no reaſon for the paſsing of this Bill.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No Reaſon?</hi> I am ſure it reacheth twentie foure <hi>Biſhops</hi> home enough although two <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> ſhould ſlip Collar, which one of them cannot, and I thinke the other ſhall not. And the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> may bee pleaſed to remember that the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons brought up Reaſons, Why <hi>Biſhops</hi> ought not to Vote in Parliament.</p>
                     <p>It cannot be denyed but that in the maine body of their Reaſons they included <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> too. And it is true, this argument reacheth not to them.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:156961:24"/> What then? did the Houſe undertake to ſtrike home even unto <hi>Arch-biſhops,</hi> in every one of their <hi>Reaſons?</hi> Where doth that appeare? It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that they have ſufficiently done it in all the reſt foregoing. If the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> thinke otherwiſe, hee ſhall be ſure to meet with more Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, in the Reaſons following. Here indeed he hath ſufficiently confuted this fourth Reaſon, as to <hi>Arch-biſhops;</hi> but it was not their good happe to get ought by the bargaine, becauſe the Houſe of Commons thought not fit to include them within the compaſſe of the Argument, which is bent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt Biſhops onely: and it is the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> to goe without his Trophee, even where he made himſelfe ſure of the Victory; for he hath fought with a ſhadow.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reason">
               <head>5. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they are but for their lives, and therefore are not fit to have Legiſlative power over the honours, inheritances, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and liberties of others.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>I. ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>Biſhops are not for their lives onely,<note place="margin">To this <hi>Reaſon</hi> a 5. fold <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> is ſhaped.</note> but for their ſucceſsors alſo, in the Land and Honour that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to their places, as the Earles and Barons alſo are for their ſucceſſors, in their owne Lands
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:156961:25"/> and honours: And, holding their Lands in fee ſimple, may with as good Reaſon Vote in the Honours, inheritance, perſons, and liberties of others, as others may and doe in theirs.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>When the Houſe of Commons ſaith, that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops <hi>are but for their lives,</hi> I conceive the Houſe to meane, that <hi>Biſhops</hi> have no right to place in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but what dies with them, (as to their heires,) without hope that their ſonnes ſhall after ſucceed them in that dignity by vertue of their birth-right, or of the fathers ſitting in Parliament before them. And that therefore,<note place="margin">In the fourth of his Reigne, <hi>Caſe of Tenures.</hi> 35. <hi>a.</hi>
                        </note> Biſhops being at firſt but caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally mounted to that height and extent of power, by <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, the more to endeere and oblige them upon all occaſions to ſerve him and his ſucceſſors in Parliament, they cannot (rationally and according to the principles of Policy and State) be hoped to be ſo carefull and reſolute in diſpoſing of their Votes, and in maintaining the priviledge, and honour of Parliaments as Temporall Lords may well be preſumed and expected to bee. For theſe being by birth-right and the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, Lords of Parliament, and one of the Eſtates of the Kingdome (without whom a Law regularly cannot palſe) they will bee more active and zealous for the good of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity that are ſure to ſucceed them in the ſame place and Honour, and to ſhare in the benefit of the prudent and faithfull diſpoſe of their preſent ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage.</p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:156961:25"/>
                     <p>But now the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> denying the <hi>Biſhops to bee for their lives only,</hi> and affirming them to be <hi>for their ſucceſſors, alſo, &amp;c.</hi> waives the ſenſe and intention of the Houſe of Commons, and diverts his Reader from the ſtrength of their Argument. For, hee tells us, that Biſhops are for their ſucceſſors, as a kinde of Corporation in Law. It is true that a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is a Corporation to ſome uſes, but that he is ſo, in reſpect of his place and Vote in Parliament, the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> hath yet neither made nor offered any proofe at all. The Biſhop is called thither by Writ to counſell the King, upon preſumption of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſufficiency and fidelity: but <hi>ubi gentium,</hi> doth it appeare, that by vertue of the fundamentall lawes of the Kingdome, the Biſhops muſt needs ſit there as a Corporation, without which the Lords Houſe cannot be full? Is it not only from Grace that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were firſt allowed place there? And if ſo, they are not immoveable out of their places, and therefore they do not neceſſarily take up thoſe places for their ſucceſſors.</p>
                     <p>But ſuppoſe they ſit there <hi>for their ſucceſſors,</hi> yet will it bee very hard to ſuppoſe the next thing too, that Biſhops are in the ſame manner there for their ſucceſſors, in the Land and Honour that pertaine to their places, <hi>as the Earles and Barons are for their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors in their owne Lands and Honours.</hi> For, is there no difference betweene Succeſſors that uſually have no naturall legitimate relation to the preſent Biſhops in any degree of conſanguinity or affinity; and thoſe of <hi>Earles</hi> and <hi>Barons,</hi> which are their proper heires at Law, and may claime and muſt enjoy the ſame Honour which their Anceſtors have held before
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:156961:26"/> them, if not tainted in bloud? No difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thoſe that can no more bee denyed place in Parliament (without confuſion of all,) than the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment thereof can be turned up by the Roots; and thoſe who firſt crept in by favour, to ſerve a Conquerors turne, by taking off their dependance upon the Pope and faſtening it upon himſelfe, and can derive no higher for ſitting (as now they doe) in the Houſe of Peeres, than an Act of Parliament, if ſo high: and therefore by another Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may be diſcharged?</p>
                     <p>Now, where the difference of the Title is ſo great, between a Biſhop and an Earle or Temporall Baron, both to their Lands and Honours, and Votes in Parliament; I much feare that the Nobility and Temporall Lords will hardly in their Houſe allow this doctrine, which yet is fitter for them to conſider of, than for me to confute: and therefore I leave it: only with this; that, if the Lords ſhall find cauſe to reject this poſition as heterodox, and deny the Biſhops to be in Parliament for their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors in Lands and Honours in the ſame manner, or upon as good and immoveable title as the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be for theirs; then, the Reaſon of the Houſe of Commons doth ſtand yet good, as to <hi>Earles and Barons,</hi> and it is no way fit that Biſhops ſhould have the ſame <hi>Legiſlative power over the Honours, inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, perſons, and liberties of Earles and Barons,</hi> as theſe have, or ought to have, over thoſe of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
                     <p>As for Biſhops <hi>holding their Lands in Fee ſimple,</hi> I can ſay little to it, becauſe my skill is very ſimple
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:156961:26"/> in <hi>Tenures.</hi> Only I have beene told that <hi>Fee-ſimple,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Littletons Inſtit.</hi> l. 1. c. 1. 5. 1. <hi>Cokus</hi> in <hi>Little. ibid. Sect.</hi> 5.</note> is called in Latine <hi>foedum ſimplex, &amp; idem eſt quod haereditas legitima vel hareditas pura.</hi> So that to ſpeak properly, <hi>Every man that hath a lawfull eſtate in Fee-ſimple hath it either by deſcent, or purchaſe:</hi> neither of which wayes, for ought I know, can the Biſhop derive his Title.</p>
                     <p>But perhaps in ſome ſenſe, wherewith I am not acquainted, the Biſhops may bee ſaid to hold in <hi>Fee-ſimple,</hi> as the word may be taken in a larger and leſſe proper acception: <hi>Viz.</hi> Becauſe he holdeth Lands in <hi>fee</hi> in right of his Church: but this is not properly <hi>Fee-ſimple,</hi> becauſe he holds them not in his owne right; and the right he hath in them, dyes with him as to his heires. But I have heard, that ordinarily, he that is ſeized of any Lands in Fee, in right of his Church, his tenure is either that which the Lawyers call <hi>Tenure per divine ſervice,</hi> when the Lands are given upon condition that the Donee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <hi>ſome divine Service certaine</hi> expreſſed in the Gift, or the Lands to revert: or elſe, it is<note n="*" place="margin">Littl. Institut. li. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>en Frank annoigne,</hi> when Lands are freely given, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any divine ſervice certaine to be performed for them.</p>
                     <p>And further; albeit the Biſhops are uſually ſaid to hold of the King <hi>per Baroniam:</hi> yet this haply may be meant rather of the <hi>Honour</hi> affixed to their place, which works it up to a Dignitie, than of the <hi>Lands</hi> pertaining to them, which they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hold in <hi>Frank almoigne,</hi> as well as the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Clergy.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sir</hi> Henry Spel. Not. in Concil. v rolam. ſub Oſſa.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hereupon it is, that in our Municipall Lawes, our Biſhops, for that they enjoy their meanes and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:156961:27"/> maintenance by the bounty and Almes of Kings, are called <hi>Barones Regis Eleemoſynarij,</hi> The Kings Lords Almeſmen, or Barons of the Kings Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moignry, as the Almeſmen at WINDSOR are called <hi>The Kings poore Knights:</hi> and the Reaſon is rendred out of <hi>Ranulphus de Glanvill,</hi> (that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Iudge in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond his time,) <hi>quia eorum Baroniae ſunt de Eleemoſyna Domini Regis &amp; Anteceſſorum ejus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">De Legib. Angl. l. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>1.</hi> in Calic.</note> Becauſe their BARONIES are of the Almes of the KING and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors.</p>
                     <p>Which being ſo, my conceit is that (what <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſo ever they have on their ſide, yet) at this time eſpecially, this free and high language, (that <hi>they holding their Lands in Fee-ſimple may with as good Reaſon Vote in the Honours, inheritance, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and liberties of others, as others may and doe in theirs</hi>) might have well beene forborne without prejudice to their Cauſe. For, if <hi>Almeſmen</hi> bee admitted to Vote in Parliament, it will bee their wiſedome, I take it, not to bee ſo much elated as to enter into termes of compariſon with the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; not excepting their Benefactors, or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders themſelves, even in one of the higheſt points of honour and power.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:156961:27"/>
                  <head>2. ANSWER to the fifth REASON.</head>
                  <q>Many Peeres have beene created for their lives only, and the Earle of Surrey for the life of his Father, who yet voted in this Houſe.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>But have any (except Biſhops) beene created Peeres for life, or otherwiſe, that were not men of great eſtates and inheritance, or at leaſt of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary birth and ſufficiency? Of ſuch eminency were the <hi>Earles</hi> of <hi>Surrey.</hi> But when you mention an <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Surrey,</hi> whom do you meane? Is it inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Noble Family of the <hi>Howards</hi> deſcended from the <hi>Mowbrayes?</hi> If of theſe, you will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde any ſuch, that being an honour not ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently communicated in former times. Indeed I I find it mentioned that <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Mowbray</hi> (Sonne of <hi>Iohn,</hi> Grand-child to <hi>Thomas</hi> Duke of Norfolke) was, by King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth in the life time of his Father, created <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Surrey,</hi> and was, after his Fathers death, Duke of <hi>Norfolke:</hi> but that he was a <hi>Peere of Parliament for, or in the life of his Father,</hi> I finde not. And I have beene told by a Noble branch of that Renowned ſtemme, and now a Peere, that there was no <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Surrey,</hi> made a Lord of Parliament upon ſuch termes. But whether ſo or ſo, it matters not much; this being but one ſingle inſtance.</p>
                     <p>And how ever you may perhaps inſtance (when you pleaſe) in others not ſo highly deſcended, who
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:156961:28"/> have had the honour to Vote as Peeres in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet they were ſuch whoſe intereſts in the publike, and ſhare in poſterity muſt needs weigh downe any of thoſe that the Houſe of Commons deſire to have removed out of the Lords Houſe. For however, diverſe of them bee well lined with wealth, yet the Houſe of Commons are in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to looke upon them, as the Lawes doe; to wit, as upon Almeſmen that are but for their owne lives: and ſurely I beleeve it will be very hard for the Anſwerer to give ſo much as any one inſtance of an Almeſman that hath beene allowed to Vote in Parliament. Not, that my purpoſe is hereby to diſparage any of that Order, in reference to their function, or preſent honours, but only to ſpeake of them as the Law it ſelfe doth, meerely and only for bolting out of the ſtrength of this branch of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the continuance of the Biſhops place and Votes as Peeres in Parliament.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <head>3. ANSVVER, to the fifth REASON.</head>
                  <q>The Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, are choſen for one Parliament only, and yet uſe their Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative power. Nor will their being elected dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference their Cauſe; for the Lords uſe that power in a greater eminence, who are not elected.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>The Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, ſit not there as ſingle men, but as the repreſentative body
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:156961:28"/> of all the Commons of England; each of them give their Votes with reference to all thoſe from whom they are ſent. Beſides, they are by the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Lawes of the Kingdome to be there, <hi>qua tales,</hi> however the Election of the particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons bee arbitrary and contingent. And although thoſe very perſons may never (perhaps) ſerve again, yet the right and inheritance of the Commons of England (whence every member of that Houſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riveth) never dyes, ſo long as the Kingdome lives. Therefore who ever, for the time hath the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to bee a Member of that ſociety, Voteth in right of the Kingdome, not of a particular man.</p>
                     <p>As for the LORDS, although they neither bee <hi>elected,</hi> nor doe Vote for any but for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their owne poſterity, yet they have this priviledge from an higher Originall, than the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops can prove themſelves to be deſcended from; namely (as wee ſaid before) not <hi>precario</hi> from Grace and favour, but from the fundamentall Lawes and Conſtitutions of the Kingdome. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, their bloud, breeding, intereſt in the publike, and care for their poſteritie borne to ſo high places, muſt needs aſſure us more of their wiſe, carefull and zealous managing of their Votes in Parliament, than can, by any prudentiall or morall grounds, be hoped from the Prelates.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="answer">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:156961:29"/>
                  <head>4. ANSWER to the fifth REASON.</head>
                  <q>A Burgeſſe, that hath a Freehold, but for terme of life only, may Vote and aſſent to a Law in Parliament.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Cokus <hi>in</hi> Litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Inſtit. Sect. <hi>133.</hi>
                        </note>The <hi>Free hold</hi> of a <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> is not by the tenure of <hi>Frank almoigne,</hi> (of which the preſent debate is) for no Lay-man can hold any Land in that tenure. Hee is therefore in that regard ſomewhat more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable.</p>
                     <p>But however this may bee, yet that which was but a little before ſaid to the next precedent Anſwer, will ſerve here alſo. A Burgeſſe doth not Vote in the Houſe of Commons as a Free-Holder (although haply none but Free-Holders or Free-men be eligible) but as a perſon choſen by and for a Burrough which hath right to ſend Burgeſſes to Parliament; and being there, he Votes by the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Laws of the Realme. Therefore it is not materiall whether his Free-hold bee for life, or for longer time. When Biſhops ſhew the like warrant and Commiſſion, or the like fundamentall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the Kingdome for their Voting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; then, this <hi>Anſwer</hi> may be welcome to the Houſe of Commons.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="answer">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:156961:29"/>
                  <head>5. ANS. to the fifth REASON.</head>
                  <q>No ſuch exception was ever heard of in the Diets of Germany, the Corteſes of Spaine, or the three Eſtates of France, where the Prelates Vote in all theſe points with the Nobility and the Commons.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>What exception hath beene taken to Biſhops in other Kingdomes, is unknowne to me, and perhaps to the Anſwerer alſo: Unleſſe he have ſeene all the Records and Journals of all thoſe Kingdomes. Nor doe I believe that the Houſe of Commons had any Reference to other Nations, nor doe intend to bee preſidented by them. As if, becauſe Biſhops have this priviledge elſewhere, therefore this muſt bee a Reaſon ſufficient for the continuing their poſſeſſion of it here. Nay, every Nation hath its proper Lawes and Cuſtomes, and though it be no ſhame to borrow any thing that is better than our owne, for the publike Weale; yet it is no Anſwer to a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon drawne from experienced inconveniency at home, to ſay that this Reaſon was never heard of in forraigne States.</p>
                     <p>But yet I thinke, if the matter were throughly examined, it will appeare that in thoſe Kingdomes, Biſhops have a kind of Soveraignty over their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Territories, and are Temporall Governours as well as ſpirituall Paſtors. And, by the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Conſtitutions of thoſe ſeveral Empires or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:156961:30"/> thoſe Biſhops doe make one of the Eſtates of the Kingdome without which a Law cannot paſſe: Sure I am, it is ſo in Germany, and I beleeve ſo or the reſt, although with ſome difference: for they may make a third Eſtate, and yet not bee ſecular or ſoveraigne Governors over their ſeverall Ditions.</p>
                     <p>Now, all know that it is farre otherwiſe with the Biſhops of England: and therefore this plea will not be of any force to breake the ſtrength of this Reaſon of the Houſe of Commons, till the Prelates can tranſlate our Lawes and Government into that of thoſe Kingdomes from whence theſe preſidents are impertinently borrowed.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reason">
               <head>6. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe of Biſhops dependency and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectancy of Tranſlations to places of greater profit.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>I. ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>This Argument ſuppoſeth all Kings, and all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to be very faulty, if they take the tune of their Votes in Parliament, from theſe depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies and expectances.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>This Argument taxeth not Kings, but medles
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:156961:30"/> only with Biſhops. It is true, Kings bring them in, and can be wiſe enough to ſerve themſelves, if they meet with men that will put themſelves to ſale for preferment. And to ſpeake plainely, the receding from the ancient way of Electing Biſhops by the Church is no ſmall occaſion and meanes to byas them, and to engage them ſtill to goe that way, which they perceive him that hath the power of electing, and of advancing them higher, to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, ſo that, if a King ſhould deſire to draw them into a wrong courſe, they ſcarce know how to deny him, nor would many of them ſticke much at it; for they being men, and ſometimes none of the beſt, are not onely ſubject to like temptations and failings that others be, but more ready and officious to ſerve turnes than many times Princes do require.</p>
                     <p>And although the Houſe of Commons doe not alwayes <hi>take the tune of Biſhops Votes in every Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from theſe dependances and expectances;</hi> yet, when they ſee how much Biſhops, that have but meane Biſhopricks, doe continually labour to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine greater, and to get up higher; and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare theſe <hi>ambitious</hi> practices with the tunes of their Votes in moſt things which concern the more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Reformation of Religion and the Clergy, and the promoting of the power of Godlineſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they cannot but find to their griefe that Biſhops Votes in Parliament, and their ambitious practices elſewhere, do too often conſort and come too neere a perfect harmony; and that therefore, there is little cauſe to pronounce them faultleſſe.</p>
                     <p>But wherein lyes the pith of this Anſwer, or, how takes it off the ſtrength of the Reaſon? Muſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:156961:31"/> the Reaſon needs be falſe becauſe it ſuppoſeth that, not which is impoſſible, but which in Civility is not fit to be ſpoken out in plaine language? The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer himſelfe doth not deny the thing to be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: therefore hee doth not <hi>Anſwer</hi> or overthrow the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but only elude it by ſtarting up a Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuppoſition which he thinkes none will dare to owne. The Reaſon then is never the worſe for this evaſion. Let us try his next.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>2. ANSWER to the fixth REASON.</head>
                  <q>This may bee ſaid of all the Kings great Officers, of all the Noble Members of both Houſes, who may bee conceived, as well as Biſhops, to have their expectances, and conſequently to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived by this Reaſon of Voting in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>Yet this anſwereth not the Argument, but only endeavours to render it odious to thoſe that were to be Iudges of it, and ſo to doe what may be to bring a prejudice upon it. It is not, I confeſſe, impoſſible that the Nobility ſhould be liable to the ſame temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:<note place="margin">Laudabilis enim vena ſuam ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit originem, &amp; fideliter poſteris tradit quae in ſe glorioſae tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsione prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit. <hi>Caſſiodor.</hi>
                        </note> yet it is not probable they ſhould ſo ſoone be borne downe before it. For, firſt, their Eſtates, generally are better, and ſo they have not that need to ſnatch at ſuch beggars baits.</p>
                     <p>Next, their bloud and Honour mounteth their minds higher and fixeth their eyes on more Noble prize, not without diſdaine to ſtoop at flyes. Laſtly,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:156961:31"/> their large ſhare in the Publike, and the ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire they have to lay a foundation for future glory to themſelves, and happineſſe to their poſterity, will make them ſcorne ſuch poore and baſe mercinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, unworthy of men borne to honour and ſtriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to purchaſe more by generous wayes, not by the ſale of Nobleneſſe and conſcience. <hi>Nobiles praemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, haud pradam petunt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <head>3. ANSWER to the ſixth REASON.</head>
                  <q>This Argument reacheth not at the two Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and ſo falls ſhort of the Votes, which are to be taken away by this Bill.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>If it had appeared that this particular <hi>Reaſon</hi> was intended againſt the Arch-Biſhops, The <hi>Anſwer</hi> had beene pertinent. But ſeeing the Houſe had no meaning, to reach ſo farre at every blow, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented it ſelfe that onely ſome of the Reaſons came home to both of them alſo, that which was ſaid before in examining the laſt <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the fourth <hi>Reaſon,</hi> is abundantly ſufficient to hold up the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this Argument againſt the aſperſion caſt upon it by this eluſory <hi>Anſwer.</hi> And yet it doth reach one of the Arch-Biſhops, by the Anſwerers good favour. An Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> would perhaps doe ſomewhat, in hope of a Tranſlation to <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="reason">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:156961:32"/>
               <head>7. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>THe ſeverall Biſhops have of late much encroached upon the Conſciences and properties of the Subject. And they and their ſucceſſors will bee much encouraged ſtill to encroach, and the Subject will be much diſcouraged from complaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch encroachments, if twentie ſixe of that Order bee to bee Iudges upon theſe complaints. The ſame Reaſon extends to their Legiſlative power, in any Bill to paſſe for the reformation of their power upon any emergent inconvenience by it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>This Argument fights not againſt Biſhops Votes in Parliament, but againſt their Votes in Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, where (if any where) they have encroa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched upon the Conſciences and properties of the Subject: Nor yet at the Vote of ſuch Biſhops there, as are not guilty of this offence. Nor need the ſubject to bee diſcouraged in complaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the like grievances, though <hi>26.</hi> of that Order continue Iudges. For they ſhall not Vote as Iudges when they are legally charged. And if they ſhould Vote, what were that to the purpoſe when the lay Peeres are ſtill foure to one? The
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:156961:32"/> Biſhops (aſsisted with a double number of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred Abbots and Priors) could not hinder the Lawes made against the Court of Rome, the Alien Cardinals and Prelates, the Proviſors, the Suitors to the Popes Conſistories under <hi>Edw. 3. Rich. 2.</hi> and <hi>Hen. 4.</hi> Much more may thoſe emergent exorbitances of the Eccleſiaſticall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction bee ſoone curbed and redreſſed in this inequalitie of Votes betweene the Temporall and Spirituall Lords. So as this Argument doth not ſo much hurt the Votes, as it quells the courage of the Biſhops, who may juſtly feare by this and the next Argument, that the taking away of their Votes is but a kind of forerunner to the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their juriſdiction.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>I know not the Reaſon, but ſo it is, that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer hath here thruſt together all hee had to ſay, into one <hi>Anſwer;</hi> although the particulars whereof it conſiſteth bee many, and of various kindes: whereas before he was pleaſed to branch out one <hi>Anſwer</hi> into many, when yet moſt of the branches were coincident. Not troubling my ſelfe to finde out the Myſtery, I ſhall make bold a little to change my Method alſo to follow him, or rather to diſtribute his Anſwers for him, and then to take a diſtinct view of the ſeverall limbes thereof a part.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <q>This Argument fights not against Biſhops Votes in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:156961:33"/> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but againſt their Votes in Convocation, where (if any where) they have encroached upon the conſciences and liberties of the Subjects.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>If <hi>this Argument fights not againſt Biſhops Votes in Parliament,</hi> why then is it ſaid, in the end of this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that <hi>Biſhops may juſtly feare, by this and the next Argument that the taking away of their votes is but a kind of forerunner to the aboliſhing of their Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction?</hi> For, what <hi>Votes</hi> are here meant, but thoſe in Parliament? and what need any feare of that here, when it is confeſſed, that <hi>this Argument fights not against</hi> Votes <hi>in Parliament?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But, I p ſſe this, becauſe contradictions in ſuch a cauſe, and in an <hi>Anſwer</hi> of ſo much length, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of ſome mens pennes, need be no matter of any admiration, or of much ſtay upon it.</p>
                     <p>But what will it availe the Biſhops that this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument meets not with them in the Parliament Houſe, ſo long as by his owne confeſſion (although a modeſt <hi>[if]</hi> would a little modifie it) it findes them out ſo palpably in <hi>Convocation.</hi> There, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, their guilt is of a double dye, for which they are now (upon examination and reſolution of both Houſes of Parliament) condemned as having voted and determined <hi>many matters contrary to the Kings Prerogative,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ex Archi. Parl.</note> 
                        <hi>to the fundamentall Lawes and Statutes of the Realme, to the right of Parliaments, to the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and libertie of the Subjects, and matters tending to ſedition and of dangerous conſequence;</hi> And as for <hi>encroaching upon</hi> and invading <hi>the conſcience,</hi> let that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:156961:33"/> abſurd, amphibolous, injurious, excerable Oath enjoyned in the ſixth <hi>Canon</hi> of their late Holy Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node ſtand for a monument, to the eternall infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the Compoſers of it, and factors, in it.</p>
                     <p>Now, the Biſhops do or ought<note place="margin">Nulli ſacerdoti liceat Canones ignorare <hi>diſt. 38 cap.</hi> Nulli.</note> to know that if a Iudge be once taken tardy and guiltie of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and wicked judgement, hee is for ever preſumed to bee corrupt, and therefore unmeet to bee truſted in another Court any more.</p>
                     <p>For, it is in Maxime both in the Civill, and Canon Lawes, which holds in all Lawes,<note place="margin">Reg. juris. <hi>8.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Semel ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ſemper praeſumitur eſſe malus.</hi> And this preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not onely <hi>praeſumptio hominis,</hi> or <hi>praeſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio facti,</hi> but <hi>praeſumptio juris</hi> too, <hi>quia jus ſic prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumit ex facto,</hi> ſaith the Gloſſe upon that rule. So that, if <hi>Biſhops have thus encroached upon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and properties of the Subject,</hi> in Convocation, as tis now declared they have, they are unmeet and unworthy to bee truſted any more with Votes in Parliament, where they may doe as much again, or more, if opportunity bee offered: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Reaſon of the Houſe of Commons is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible.</p>
                     <p>But have they not done as much in Parliament alſo? What meant the Statute of 2. <hi>H.</hi> 4.15. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lollards procured by <hi>Thomas Arondel</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the reſt of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates againſt diverſe of the Nobilitie; for, they are not at all mentioned in that Act? What meant their ſtruggling for the ſixe Articles in 31. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 14. firſt concluded in their Holy Synod in ſpite of <hi>CRANMERS</hi> teeth? What meant their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy to pull downe Religion in 1. <hi>Mar.</hi> after it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:156961:34"/> had happily in great part beene reformed in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his time? What need we any further proofe? <hi>Habemus confitentem,</hi> this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer himſelfe hath confeſſed as much in the cloſe of his <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the next <hi>Reaſon</hi> following, where he roundly acknowledgeth <hi>the oppoſition of all the Biſhops to the Reformation of Religion</hi> in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> But I muſt on to the reſt of the <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">Nor yet at the Votes of ſuch Biſhops there, as are not guilty of that offence.</q> That is, of paſſing ſuch Canons in Convocation.</p>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>This Exception may ſave the Credits of thoſe men who were preſent, and proteſted legally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch illegall and wicked proceedings; ſo as, they may have peace within, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out too, if after by poſt-fact they contracted not the guilt of Acceſſories, by adminiſtring thoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons: But yet, in the account of Law, and in the eſtimate of Law-makers, before whom ſuch lewd Canons bee arraigned, the Biſhops doe know that it is another Maxime and Rule in Law, <hi>Refertur ad univerſos quod publice fit per majorem partem,</hi> That is juſtly imputed to all that was publikely done by the Major part. If they who diſſented not, did not proteſt, in due forme of Law, or abſented themſelves becauſe they diſliked the buſineſſe, but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:156961:34"/> had not the courage and fidelity to oppoſe it as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their duty; they are juſtly involved within the number of the guilty, at leaſt ſo far, as to be held unworthy to be any further truſted to Vote either in that place, or in an higher much more, becauſe through negligence, incogitancy, cowardiſe, and the like, they did not their utmoſt to helpe the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty, and to oppoſe thoſe wicked Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons with all their might. I paſſe on to the next branch of the Anſwer.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>Nor need the Subject to be diſcouraged in complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the like grievances, though twentie ſixe of that Order continue Iudges. For they ſhall not Vote as Iudges in their own Cauſe, when they are legally charged.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>What encouragement ſhall one, or ſome few private ſubjects hope to finde, when the whole Houſe of Commons, by the labouring of ſome Prelates (leſſe in number than twenty ſixe,) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get paſſage for a neceſſary Bill grounded upon ſo many ſolid and weighty <hi>Reaſons,</hi> againſt the Votes of Biſhops in Parliament? And who can be aſſured that hereafter <hi>they ſhall not vote as Iudges in their owne Cauſe,</hi> when even now <hi>de facto,</hi> they have already done it?</p>
                     <p>Perhaps there is a ſecret in that clauſe <hi>[When they are legally charged]</hi> which I cannot diſcover.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:156961:35"/> But ſurely, I thinke the meaning of it to be, that the Bill came not home to a <hi>legall charge</hi> that might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them from votcing in it, becauſe the Houſe of Commons would needs be ſo civill towards the preſent Biſhops, as not to name them in the Bill; whereby, not their perſons, but their Order onely was charged. And if this were the error upon which the firſt Bill miſcarried, the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons are wiſe enough to make uſe of this cloſe wipe of the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> and to finde out a way to avoyd the like fault in the next. The Anſwerer goes on.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>And if they ſhould vote, what were that to the purpoſe, when the Lay-Peeres are ſtill foure to one?</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>If the Lay-Peeres (as he termeth them) were tenne to one, yet if but a few of thoſe twentie ſixe Biſhops have a mind to be active (which, in their own cauſe, is not unlikely) they know wayes enough how to draw over to their party Noble and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous natures apt to be more taken with reverence of their function and gravity, than willing to ſuſpect their ends or to diſpute their grounds, how often ſo ever themſelves or their Anceſtors have beene cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented and miſguided by them.</p>
                     <p>But he will give you inſtances to the contrary, which may put all out of feare.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="answer">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:156961:35"/>
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>The Biſhops (aſsiſted with a double number of Mitred Abbots and Priors) could not hinder the Lawes made gainſt the Cou t of Rome, the Alien Cardinals, and Prelates, the Prov ſors, the Suitors to the Popes Conſiſtory under <hi>Edw. 3. Ric. 2.</hi> and <hi>Hen. 4.</hi> much more may thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergent exorbitancies of the Eccleſiaſticall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction be ſoon curbed &amp; redreſſed in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality of votes betweene the Temporall and Spirituall Lords.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Biſhops (ſo aſsiſted) could not hinder?</hi> Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they could not hinder the Lawes made againſt the Pope, &amp; Strangers. For, the more the Pope en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croached, the more our Biſhops ſmarted under thoſe Vſurpations, and groaned under the many &amp; continuall heavy taxes whereby all the Clergy of England were impoveriſhed in their Eſtates, and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> much curbed in their Iuriſdictions. He ſhould ſhew himſelfe an egregious Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro to the Stories of thoſe times, that ſhould require Inſtances hereof, there being ſo many, much elder than <hi>Edward</hi> the third: <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> and ſundry other Hiſtorians abound herein. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will content my ſelfe with only one inſtance in the reigne of <hi>Hen</hi> 3.</p>
                     <p>In his time the exactions &amp; pollings of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and Kingdome were found to be yearly 60000<note place="margin">Antiq Britan. ex Mat. Paris. in Bonifac.</note>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:156961:36"/> Markes, which, at that time, exceeded the Kings owne Revenues. No benefice, or dignity belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Nobility, Clergy, or Gentry, not many pertaining to the King himſelfe could bee void, but the Popes <hi>Proviſors</hi> were ready to ſeize on it inſtantly for ſome of his Creatures, Italians and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forraigners. The Biſhops fretted, but durſt not complaine. When the King ſaw their timorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the whole Kingdome heightned up to ſuch a degre of diſcontent, that they threatned to caſt off their obedience to the King, if he tooke not order to caſe them;<note place="margin">The letters Articles are ſet downe at large in <hi>Math. Paris.</hi> in <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. pag 927. <hi>&amp;c. edit. Lond. Anno.</hi> 1571.</note> a Parliament was called; the King, the Nobility, Prelates, Commons, all complained of the unſupportableneſſe of the burden; drew up their greivances into ſeaven ſeverall Articles; foure letters were conceived and ſent with theſe greivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Pope; one from the Biſhops, a ſecond from the Abbots, a third from the Nobility and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and the fourth from the King himſelfe; but, to little purpoſe. The Pope ſtill went on, although ſometimes more favourably, and other times more violently, as the times would ſuffer.</p>
                     <p>No marvell then, if Biſhops and Abbots in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament were ſo willing to be over-borne by the votes of the temporall Lords in paſſing the Statute of Proviſors of benefices, in 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>and againſt ſuitors to the Popes Conſiſtory, and receiving of Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from Rome in</hi> 38. Ed. 3 <hi>And againſt the farming of any Benefices enjoyed by Aliens</hi> by the Popes Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>or conveing of mony to them.</hi> 3. Ric. 2, 3. And againſt <hi>Going out of the Realme to procure a Benefice in this Realme</hi> in 12, Ric. 2.15. And for confirmation of the Statute <hi>de proviſoribus</hi> among the Statutes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:156961:36"/> called <hi>Other Statutes made at Westminſter. in</hi> 13. <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. ca. 2. The like may be ſaid of the Statute of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion</hi> in 2. <hi>Hen,</hi> 4.4 <hi>of firſt fruites to Rome more than uſuall.</hi> 6 <hi>H.</hi> 4.1 <hi>Of moneys carryed to Rome,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all Statutes <hi>againſt Proviſors &amp;c.</hi> 9. Hen. 4 8. To ſay nothing of that famous Statute in 26. Hen. 8.21. which gave the Pope a deeper wound than all the Acts that had been before.</p>
                     <p>Now, alas poore Biſhops that they were ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-voted that they could not hinder ſuch Lawes as thoſe, made in their favour, and for the reſcuing of them from the Italian horſe-leeches! No doubt the Biſhops laboured ſtoutly to withſtand theſe Acts: and therefore no marvaile that they be ſo carefully inſtanced in, or pointed unto by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer, to ſhew how eaſily Biſhops may bee over-voted in Parliament and how ſoon emergent exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies of their Iuriſdiction may be there curbed &amp; redreſſed. Or rather indeed to ſhew how unable Biſhops bee to withſtand the paſſing of a bill which they deſire with all their hearts may bee enacted, or which they know the King wil have to be enacted. But otherwiſe, I cannot underſtand his reaſon in vouching of them: unleſſe he meant to make his Readers ſome mirth. See now how hee winds up this long Anſwere.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>So as this Argument doth not ſo much hurt the votes, as it quells the courage of the Biſhops, who may justly feare, by this and the next Argument that the taking away of their Votes is but a kind
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:156961:37"/> of fore-runner to the aboliſhing of their Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>Indeed, if we take the ſcantling of the <hi>hurt</hi> done to their <hi>Votes,</hi> by the inſtances produced in this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> the hurt is ſo little, that the adventure will not bee great, if they meet with other Bills in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of like nature, wherin the Temporall Lords ſhall happen to over-vote them. In thoſe Statutes before mentioned, I doe not finde the Clergy ſo much as named. It is probable, they durſt not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare for thoſe Acts, for feare of the Pope; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffered them to paſſe, by the Temporall votes, that they might the better excuſe it at Rome, and enjoy the benefit with more ſecurity at home, when the Temporalty alone were ſo ready to doe it to their hands.</p>
                     <p>Iuſt ſo it was in <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds time, when the Pope had compelled the Biſhops to ratifie all the Grants of payments to Rome made by <hi>K. Iohn,</hi> whereby the Biſhops were ſo caſt betweene the mil-ſtones, as to be ready to be ground to powder, yet durſt not appeare againſt their oppreſſor, they (Good men) were forced by the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment much againſt their wills <hi>(Si placet)</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued out of his hands without any labour of their owne; when, firſt the King profeſſed <hi>ſe contra infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos illos et timidos Epiſcopos pro Regni libertate ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Antiq. Britan. in Bonif.</note> 
                        <hi>nec cenſum deinceps ullum Romanae curiae praeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum.</hi> And afterward, when the whole Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ordered the Biſhops and Abbots to write to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:156961:37"/> his Holineſſe that which with all their hearts they would, if they durſt, have done of themſelves, for obtaining eaſe of the burthens that lay upon them, as hath been touched before.</p>
                     <p>So that now, this Argument doth little <hi>quell their courage,</hi> if they meet with no greater diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements than by the anſwerer hath been ſet forth. Rather the <hi>Anſwere</hi> teacheth them the way how to prevaile by being overcome, and to bring about their owne ends and yet ſit ſtill, or ſeeme to be the greateſt oppoſers of that which in ſecret they moſt deſire, and underhand doe moſt labour for.</p>
                     <p>But truly, it is to me no leſſe than a riddle, that there ſhould be any juſt cauſe of feare (unleſſe unto them who are apt to <hi>feare wher no feare is</hi>) that there is any thing in this Argument tending to the <hi>Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of Epiſcopal Iuriſdiction;</hi> when the Reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſuppoſeth no more, but a <hi>Bill to paſse for the Regulation of their power upon any emergent inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience by it.</hi> Verily there is more cauſe of feare on the other ſide, that if the mention of a bill for <hi>regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating</hi> the power of Biſhops ſhall be interpreted a plot to ruine their Iuriſdiction, which now is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant, their Caſe comes very neere to that of old Rome,<note place="margin">Liv. Hist Dec. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note> which (as <hi>Livy</hi> obſerves) could noe longer ſtand under the vices committed in it, nor endure the remedies applied to it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="reason">
               <head>8. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>Becauſe the whole number of them is intereſſed to maintaine the juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Biſhops; which hath beene found ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:156961:38"/> greivous to the three Kingdomes, that Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land hath utterly aboliſhed it, &amp; multitudes in England and Ireland have petitioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>This Argument is not against the Votes of Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops, but againſt Epiſcopacy it ſelfe, which must bee removed, becauſe Scotland hath done ſo, and ſome in England and Ireland would have it ſo; And yet peradventure ten times as great a ſomme as theſe deſire the contrary.<note place="margin">Againſt this a 2 fold <hi>Anſwer</hi> is offered.</note>
                  </q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>This <hi>Argument</hi> is expreſly <hi>againſt their votes for maintaining their Iuriſdiction,</hi> (to which by their Order they are all bound, as all other ſocieties bee, to maintaine their Priviledges;) and it is not bent <hi>againſt Epiſcopacy it ſelfe.</hi> And yet this ſuggeſtion is a witty invention, both to winde out of the ſtrength of this <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and to caſt a blurre upon it at the farewell.</p>
                     <p>The Houſe of Commons could not but ſee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven an impoſſibility of reforming by bill the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and intolerable exorbitancies of the preſent tyranny of many <hi>Biſhops</hi> (who diſhoneſtly cal it by the honeſt name of <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi>) ſo long as the <hi>Biſhops</hi> be ſuffered to vote in Parliament. For the <hi>Biſhops</hi> bee themſelves the greateſt Offenders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, either acting in it, or elſe (as <hi>Galba</hi>) wittingly permitting thoſe to uſurpe whom they ought to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:156961:38"/> bridle, or willingly ignorant of what they ought to know. Therefore it was deſired that their Votes in Parliament might be taken away, to make paſſage for another <hi>Bill</hi> that might <hi>regulate their Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as in the former <hi>Reaſon</hi> was plainely intimated. <hi>But the Anſwerer</hi> was willing to ſlide over that which was the life of the preſent <hi>Reaſon, (viz.</hi> the engagement of <hi>Biſhops</hi> to <hi>maintaine their juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, id est,</hi> as now it ſtandeth) and <hi>Lap-wing</hi> like to carry his Readers from the neſt, to gaize upon the deſtruction of Epiſcopacy it ſelfe, which on my conſcience was not then intended by the Houſe of Commons, had that firſt <hi>Bill</hi> been quietly yeelded by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the Houſe of Peeres.</p>
                     <p>Nor did the Houſe of Commons, I preſume, by the inſtance of Scotland, and of thoſe in England and Ireland intend, in this <hi>Reaſon,</hi> a purpoſe of Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of the Calling, but onely made uſe of it as an Argument <hi>a majore ad minus:</hi> to this effect: That, if <hi>the Iuriſdiction of Biſhops</hi> (as now they terme it) be found ſo greivous, that, in Scotland they would endure Epiſcopacy it ſelfe no longer; and, many in England, and Ireland have petitioned for the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of it in theſe other Kingdomes; it cannot be thought unreaſonable and immodeſt for the Houſe of Commons to paſſe a <hi>Bill</hi> for a leſſer matter, to witt, for taking away the <hi>Votes</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; without which there is little or no hope that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> will ever ſuffer an other <hi>Bill</hi> to bee ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for the thorough Reformation and regulating of their Iuriſdiction, ſo as to give eaſe of the many Greivances that ſtill ly upon the ſubjects of both Kingdomes of England, and Ireland, and to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:156961:39"/> the Petitioners with Reaſon worthy of ſuch a Parliament, at ſuch a time of generall diſcontent, cheifly cauſed by the uſurpations of ſundry Biſhops and of their domineering party.</p>
                     <p>What is in the <hi>Anſwer</hi> (with ſhew of modeſty) ſaid, that <hi>peradventure ten times as many deſire</hi> the continuance of Epiſcopacy, as there be Petitioners againſt it, It might peradventure be ſo, before the <hi>Biſhops</hi> procured that firſt bill grounded upon theſe Reaſons, to be rejected above; and before the world was made acquainted with that <hi>Abſtract of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers</hi> given to them. But I dare ſay, that now, without all <hi>peradventure,</hi> (if we may judge of mens deſires by their expreſſions) there is, ſcarce one of ten, who before were for <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> reformed, but are now againſt it: the reaſon is, becauſe they ſee there is no hope, that ever the <hi>Biſhops</hi> will cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully yeeld to a perfect Reformation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Order, and that if hereafter the Prelates ſhould happen (againſt their will) to bee over ruled in it, ſuch a forced Reformation will never doe good, nor ſecure the Kingdome againſt the Evills too long ſuſtained under them, if the Calling it ſelfe be continued.</p>
                     <p>And verily, no one thing hath more alienated &amp; exaſperated the hearts of all ſorts, than the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended inſufficiencies of theſe printed <hi>Anſwers</hi> to the <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the Houſe of Commons. So that, if <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> happen to miſcarry, I am perſwaded, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> will find Cauſe to aſcribe the opening of ſo ſpeedy a way to their deſtruction, not to any thing ſo much as to the unhappy <hi>Anſwers</hi> given to theſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the Houſe of Commons; if thoſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:156961:39"/> 
                        <hi>Anſwers</hi> offered to the Houſe of Lords were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or better than they are preſented to publike view in that more unhappy Abſtract moſt unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly printed.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>2. ANSVVER to the eighth REASON.</head>
                  <q>There wil be found Peeres enough in the Vpper Houſe to reforme any thing amiſſe in the Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, although the <hi>26.</hi> Prelates ſhould bee ſo wicked as to oppoſe it: As there were found Peeres enough in that Noble Houſe to curb the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Revenues of the Cardinals un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Edw. 3.</hi> To meet with the Proviſors under <hi>Rich. 2.</hi> To put all the Clergie into a <hi>Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire</hi> under <hi>Hen. 8.</hi> And to reforme the Religion <hi>1 Eliz.</hi> notwithſtanding the oppoſition of all the Biſhops.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>Mark here his <hi>Plea in Barre</hi> againſt the Bill, There were Peeres enough <hi>to curb the Court of Rome,</hi> in <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. when none were more glad of the curbing of that Court, than our Biſhops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>Ergo</hi> there will ever be found Peeres enough to reforme the Biſhops juriſdiction. I will not ſay of this putting our <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction</hi> and the <hi>Court of Rome</hi> ſo neere together, <hi>Pares cum parihas facillime congregantur.</hi> But it will perhaps make ſport to ſome to finde them in this <hi>Abſtract</hi> ſo cloſe one by another: yet can it not ſecure wiſe men, that becauſe the Peeres curbed the Pope, <hi>Ergo</hi> there will ever be enough to curb our Biſhops; unleſſe the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:156961:40"/> will yeeld themſelves to hold of the Pope, or to be of the ſame ſtamp, and reſolve to riſe and fall with him.</p>
                     <p>As for thoſe Cole-worts in <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. now a ſecond time heated, I referre the Reader who deſires a freſh taſte of them, to the <hi>Examination</hi> of the former <hi>Anſwer.</hi> In the caſe of <hi>Premunire,</hi> in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. who knowes not that (if any ſuch had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Parliament) the Clergie were not ſo much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verborn by the Nobility, as overawed by that ſtern and ſtout King, with whom the proudeſt Prelate durſt not to conteſt? But when wil it be proved that this paſſed in Parliament? Surely <hi>Holinſhed</hi> &amp; others tell me that the Biſhops were called into the Kings Bench about it, but before their day of appearance, there was a <hi>Convocation,</hi> wherein it was concluded that the Clergie of the Province of <hi>Canterbury</hi> ſhould offer 100000. pound for compoſition, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was accepted, and a pardon promiſed to paſſe in Parliament to free them of the <hi>Premunire.</hi> So in 7. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the Convocation incurred a <hi>Premunire</hi> for citing one <hi>Standiſh</hi> to appeare before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, when they had not juriſdiction: which yet was compounded and no Act of Parliament paſſed on it: Nor needed there an Act for it, for the Biſhops themſelves confeſſed the thing and ſo it could not come to a conteſt in the Parliament. This is all that I know of this matter. And if the caſe be thus this inſtance is not to the purpoſe. But the laſt is of all other the moſt impertinent, and ſcandalous.</p>
                     <p>Impertinent, becauſe all the world knowes that the Reformation of Religion was the deſigne
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:156961:40"/> of the Queene whom the Prelates might not croſſe; ſuch as did thwart were duely rewarded for their paines, as hath beene formerly touched. Therefore untill it can bee found that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were over Voted in a Cauſe wherein the PRINCE went with them, or expected their aſſiſtance, to Vote for him, the force of the Reaſon is not abated.</p>
                     <p>Next, what a ſcandall to Biſhops is it, that even ſince the Reformation begun in <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his time, the Biſhops, all the Biſhops ſhould oppoſe the reſtauration thereof in the beginning of Queene <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> after an interruption of ſcarce five yeares and an halfe! Surely, if Biſhops can ſo farre degenerate in ſo ſhort a time, they are hardly to bee truſted with Voting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for any long continuance, eſpecially in an age of ſuch a poſtatiſing of the moſt, and warping of the beſt.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="reason">
               <head>IX. REASON of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe Biſhops being Lords of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it ſetteth too great a diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and the reſt of their Brethren in the Miniſtery, which occaſioneth pride in them, diſcontent in others, and diſquiet in the Church.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <q>This is an Argument from Morall Philoſophy, which affords no Demonstrations. All are
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:156961:41"/> not proud that Vote in Parliament, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented which are not ſo imployed. This Argument fights onely againſt their Title of being LORDS, which is not the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion at this time. And were thoſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſo wiſe and well affected as they might be, they would rejoyce rather that ſome of their owne profeſsion are advanced to thoſe places wherein they may bee capable, upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of doing good offices to them, and to this whole Church.</q>
                  <div type="examination">
                     <head>EXAMEN.</head>
                     <p>The firſt note is but a peece of mirth, which is but little <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of any great <hi>Morality,</hi> in a Cauſe ſo ſerious. <hi>If all bee not proud that vote in Parliament,</hi> they have the more cauſe to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God that keepes them humble in ſo great a temptation. Yet, uſually, all be not humble who ſay they are not proud. Proud men of all others will be leaſt knowne of Pride. The <hi>Reaſon</hi> doth not ſay, that all are proud who Vote, but only that ſuch high dignity (not meet for them) occaſioneth pride, and I hope it will not bee denyed by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to be a rule of <hi>Divinity</hi> as well as of <hi>Morall Philoſophy,</hi> that apparent and experienced occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſinne muſt bee avoyded as well as the ſinne it ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, this <hi>Anſwerer</hi> takes no notice of the maine baſis of the Argument, which is, that <hi>this ſetteth too great a diſtance betweene the Biſhops and the reſt of their Brethren.</hi> And to ſay truth, there
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:156961:41"/> was no great Reaſon why hee ſhould, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Principles of Prelates, which will never ſuffer them to ſubſcribe to the truth of ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. They never thinke the <hi>diſtance to be too great,</hi> betweene themſelves, and the inferiour Clergie. And the neerer to parity, the neerer to Hereſie. Yet, becauſe this is an opinion not very fit to bee ſpoken out, it was good policy to paſſe over this branch in ſilence: and, it were ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to labour in the aſſerting of that which the <hi>Anſwer</hi> doth not gain-ſay.</p>
                     <p>And though, <hi>all bee not diſcontented, that are not ſo imployed:</hi> for ſome of them are Chaplaines, Dependants, Expectors, Pretenders to the like places, and ſo cannot but rejoyce to ſee them on Cock-Horſe, who will, they hope, one day give them the hand to lift them up behind them. Yet there bee many moe who have more cauſe of juſt <hi>diſcontent</hi> at the infinite clation, intolerable pride, and boundleſſe paſſions of ſome of the Biſhops, who looking up to their owne Lordly Titles, doe take it for a part of their honour to looke downe upon their poore brethren with ſo much ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, as if they were not brethren but ſervants, yea ſlaves, <hi>ad ſervitutem natos,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Tiberius, <hi>Tacit</hi>
                        </note> as Hee ſaid of his ſubiugated fellow Senators of Rome.</p>
                     <p>Before this Lording in Parliament came up, the old Rule among Biſhops was,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Con. Carthag.</hi> 4. ca. 34.</note> 
                        <hi>Epiſcopus in quolibet loco ſedens ſtare Presbyterum non patiatur.</hi> But that Canon is now 1240. yeares old, and ſo may well be forgotten. Now, it is well if he may after long atttendance bee admitted into the preſence of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, where he muſt ſtand bare headed, while the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:156961:42"/> Biſhop ſits, or perhaps lyes along in State. And whereas before, they were not aſhamed to call and honour them as <hi>Brethren,</hi> now they have other names for them, <hi>Dunce, Aſſe, Foole, Iack, Rogue, Scotiſh ſpirited raſcall,</hi> any thing that a tongue ſet on fire of Hell can belch out.</p>
                     <p>Lo here the goodly fruit of Epiſcopacie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the heigth of Peerage in Parliament! and wel were it for many of them and their poore Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, if this were the worſt and greateſt cauſe of griefe and diſcontent adminiſtred by the Biſhops to many grave, Godly, painefull, peaceable Miniſters, whoſe heavie burdens are preſented in multitudes of Petitions to the preſent Parliament, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I forbeare to relate them.</p>
                     <p>But where it is ſaid that <hi>this Argument</hi> of the Houſe of Commons <hi>fights only againſt their Title of Lords:</hi> the <hi>Anſwer</hi> miſreports it: For it marcheth (not fighteth) againſt them as <hi>Lords of Parliament:</hi> now, if to be a Lord in Parliament, and to Vote as Peeres there be not the ſame thing, the Anſwer is worthy of Conſideration: otherwiſe, it can expect no entertainment, but neglect. The Houſe of Commons did purpoſely uſe this phraſe here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the very <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelfe is grounded, partly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Title, yet ſo, as that they conſider a Biſhop as a Peere admitted to Vote in Parliament. Theſe two are convertible and equipollent expreſſions; He is a Lord of Parliament, <hi>Ergo,</hi> he Votes. He Votes in Parliament, <hi>Ergo,</hi> a Lord of Parliament. And this Lordſhip in Parliament is that which lifts him up ſo high above his brethren, as makes him to be, and they to fare the worſe all dayes of his life.</p>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:156961:42"/>
                     <p>Wherefore, to conclude all; ſuch is my folly that I know not what <hi>wiſedome, or good affection</hi> it were, for <hi>thoſe Brethren to rejoyce</hi> much, to ſee any <hi>of their owne Profeſsion</hi> to bee expoſed to ſo great temptations, by being advanced to that place, which is ſo farre from rendring them <hi>capable</hi> or apt to <hi>doe good offices</hi> to either Church or State, as that it makes them more unapt unto, and uncapable of doing any good at all, either in Parliament, Pulpit, or Conſiſtory. For it puts them out of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, unapts them for the proper worke of it, and is, not ſeldome, ſecretly followed, by the juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of GOD, with a ſpirit of coldneſſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numdneſſe of thoſe excellent parts wherewith ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them before abounded, with a ſpirit of gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe in point of judgment, with a ſpirit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thoſe Ordinances which formerly they prized, in point of affection, with a ſpirit of pride over their brethren in point of behaviour, with a ſpirit of perſecution of the power of godlineſſe in point of juriſdiction, and with a ſpirit of oppoſition to the perfect <hi>Reformation</hi> of this <hi>whole Church,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">See the cloſe of laſt prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                        </note> in point of Legiſlative power in Parliament.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ERGO,</hi> Biſhops ought not to Vote in Parliament.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pag. 2. <hi>l.</hi> 28. after <hi>acceptat,</hi> there ſhould be a ſhort line, thus;— as implying ſome words omitted which in the Author be interpoſed <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>r. indicare, p.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>r. avocation, p.</hi> 34. <hi>l. ult. r.</hi> 18. <hi>ibid.</hi> in Mar. dele 1317. &amp; <hi>r. M.</hi> 17. <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>r.</hi> could, <hi>p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r. nati.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
